<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="98"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[2017
            2018
Curriculum Catalog

                                  Mr. Robert V. Parker
                                  Superintendent
                                  Madison City Schools

                                        0]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Madison City Schools

                  Curriculum Catalog 2017-2018

Madison City Schools Vision and Mission              ...........................................2

Scheduling Definitions .................................................................................................................. 3

Points of Academic Interest .......................................................................................................... 4

• Advanced Placement

• Honors/PreAP

• ACCESS Distance Learning Program

• Options Open

Procedures Related to Grades and Credits................................................................................. 5

• Deficiencies

• Schedule Change vs Schedule Correction

• Partial Completion

• Transfer Students

• Transfer of Grades into System

• Early Completion

• Graduation Participation

• Selection of Valedictorian and Salutatorian

• NCAA Requirements for College Athletes

• Grading Scale

• Dual Enrollment

Graduation Requirements ............................................................................................................ 8

Madison City Diploma Endorsements........................................................................................ 10

Frequently Asked Questions .................................................................................................. 10

Courses and Course Descriptions

The ACADEMIES OF CAREER TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION ................................................... 13

The ARTS ...................................................................................................................................... 29

ENGLISH ....................................................................................................................................... 34

HEALTH, PHYSICAL EDUCATION & DRIVER’S ED .................................................................. 39

MATH ............................................................................................................................................. 40

• Math Recommended Course Map

SCIENCE ....................................................................................................................................... 45

SOCIAL SCIENCE......................................................................................................................... 49

SPECIAL SERVICES..................................................................................................................... 53

WORLD LANGUAGE .................................................................................................................... 57

Bob Jones Registration Dates .................................................................................................... 61

James Clemens Registration Dates ........................................................................................... 62

AP Agreement............................................................................................................................... 63

Dual Enrollment Application ....................................................................................................... 64

Early or Mid-Year Completion Application ................................................................................ 65

Credit Recovery Information        . ....................................................................................... 66

Bob Jones Registration Form for Cohort 2021          . 67

Bob Jones Registration Form for Cohorts 2018-2020    69

James Clemens Registration Form for Cohort 2021 ................................................................ 71

James Clemens Registration Form for Cohorts 2018-20  73

MCS Virtual Learning Option                          . 75

MCS Options Open           .                         . 78

MCS Options Open Registration Form ..                . 79

MCS Virtual Option Agreement       . ..              . 80

MCS Virtual Option Registration Form ..              . 82

NCAA Athletic Eligibility          . ....................................................................................... 83

Diploma Checklists for Graduation        .......................................................................... 91

FERPA Notice ............................................................................................................................... 92

Dual Enrollment Approved Courses .......................................................................................... 93

                                         1]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Madison City Schools

Vision:
Empowering students for global success.
Mission:
Madison City Schools (MCS), with effective leadership and community cooperation, will provide all students a nurturing
environment, an uncompromising excellence in instruction, a relevant and rigorous curriculum and state-of-the-art facilities
so that they can achieve their fullest potential, strive toward global learning, compete globally in the work force and contribute
positively to society.
PROCESS OF SCHEDULING
The Semester Block Schedule is based on four approximately ninety-six minute classes per day. A student will take four
courses in the fall and four different courses in the spring. With the start of the 2015-2016 school year, students will have
the opportunity to take courses outside of the traditional school day. Madison City is piloting online courses and a zero and
fifth block course that will provide more opportunities for our students and add an element of flexibility to their schedules.
While we are now in our second year of the pilot, course options will be limited.
Generally students are scheduled for courses so that at least two academic required core courses are taken each semester.
Additional electives or additional core courses may complete the remaining blocks in the schedule each semester. Teachers
will begin teaching on the first day; therefore, it is extremely important for students to come prepared for class on the first
day of each semester. Students will have fewer courses at a time but should be prepared to concentrate more on the
courses and use time wisely. Students planning to apply to select colleges may want to incorporate more than two core
subjects each semester. Please see the College Advisor if you have questions.
After you have studied the requirements for your graduating class, the curriculum, and course descriptions, you will be ready
to make decisions for your individual class schedule. At the end of this catalog, you will find Course Request Forms by
Cohort Group for your upcoming year at Bob Jones and James Clemens. As you will see in the curriculum selections,
courses are nine or eighteen weeks long. As you practice filling in the blocks to establish your schedule, keep in mind the
length of time for each course. How you fill in the blocks and register for classes does not guarantee that you will have those
classes at any specific time, only that you will have the class or an alternate selection. Be sure that you have requested 8
full credits of study and all alternative courses.

                                                                                 2]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[SCHEDULING DEFINITIONS

Graduation Cohort  The student’s graduation year
Block Schedule
Credit             Schedule based on approximately four ninety-six minute class periods per day.
Fall Semester
                   A unit of academic work (Carnegie Unit) requiring 140 hours of instruction.

                   The first and second nine-week terms of the school year (18 weeks). Students will take and can
                   earn four credits.

Spring Semester    The third and fourth nine-week terms of the school year (18 weeks). Students will take four new
                   courses beginning in January and can earn four credits.

Course             A unit of instruction.
Core Courses
                   Those courses required for graduation as identified by the Alabama Administrative Code.
                   (English, Math, Science, and Social Science)

Corequisite        A course of study required to be taken simultaneously with another.

Prerequisite       A course of study that must be “passed” to move forward in a sequence of courses.

Teacher Approval   Approval required when there is a definite screening process (i.e. audition or
                   application).

Online Course      Online learning, sometimes referred to as e-learning, is a form of distance education. Online
                   courses are delivered over the Internet and can be accessed from a computer with a Web browser
                   (ex. Internet Explorer).

Zero Block         Courses offered during a zero block will occur before the official school day begins.

Fifth Block        Courses offered during a fifth block will occur after the official school day ends.

Course Selection
Complete your registration form and obtain any necessary signatures. This form will be kept in your student portfolio for
future reference during your time as a student in Madison City Schools. Students planning to attend college are
encouraged to contact several colleges in which they are interested to determine the academic requirements for
admission. This should be done early and reviewed each year.

Points of Academic Interest
Curriculum consists of core courses which are required in order to move forward to advanced academic studies or
additional electives. Elective courses offered in each department allow students’ enrollment into courses that are
interesting to them. A good background can be achieved for each student, whether they plan to enroll in a two or four year
college or enter the workforce following graduation.

Advanced Placement (AP)
Advanced Placement courses are accelerated in rigor and pace. Advanced Placement (AP) allows students to complete
college level studies while in high school.

                   3]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Points of Academic Interest

The VALUE of Advanced Placement
     • More than 90% of four-year institutions in the United States grant credit, advanced placement, or both on the basis
          of qualifying AP exam scores. For more information visit the following website:

         www.collegeboard.com/ap/creditpolicy.

     • AP course experience favorably impacts 85% of admission decisions of selective colleges and universities.
     • AP coursework increases scholarship opportunity and improves chances of college admission.
     • The cost of the AP exam is less than most college textbooks.
     • Students who take AP courses and exams are much more likely than their peers to complete a college degree on

          schedule in 4 years. (An additional year can cost your family on average between $18,000 - $29,000). For more
          information visit www.collegeboard.com/research
     • AP prepares students majoring in engineering, biochemistry and other STEM (science, technology, engineering,
          mathematics) majors in college.
     • AP students perform better in their intermediate-level STEM coursework than students with the same SAT score
          who had taken the college’s own introductory course.
“One of the best standard predictors of academic success at Harvard is performance on Advanced Placement
Examinations.” - William Fitzsimmons, Dean of Admissions & Financial Aid, Harvard University

Students participating in Advanced Placement are required to take the National AP Exam as part of the courses’ curriculum.
This testing fee (approx. $95) may be reduced or waived based solely upon the guidelines articulated by the Alabama State
Department of Education for free/reduced lunches. Therefore, no student will be denied participation in the AP Program due
to financial hardship. It is highly recommended that students consult with college(s) of choice, as college credit may be
earned by scoring a 3, 4, or 5 on the exam. Careful attention should be given when selecting an AP course or courses
as students will not be allowed to drop an AP course. Consult the grading scale to view the weight given to rigor of the
AP program. All students who register for an AP class should complete the required agreement (included in the back of the
curriculum catalog) and return with the registration form.

Honors/PreAP
Honors courses are designed for the college-bound student. The curriculum is covered at an accelerated pace and provides
students the opportunity to take advanced-level courses in English, world languages, math, and science. These courses
follow the Alabama Course of Study and include enrichment activities, extra projects, research, and/or laboratory
experiences. Honors and PreAP courses are noted in the course descriptions and receive Honors weighted credit per the
current grading scale. Careful attention should be made when selecting an honors course. Students will not be allowed
to drop Honors/PreAP courses. Consult the grading scale to view the weight given to rigor of the Honors/PreAP/AP
program.

ACCESS Distance Learning Program
Madison City participates in the ACCESS (Alabama Connecting Classrooms Educators and Students Statewide) Distance
Learning, a program sponsored by the Alabama Department of Education to connect teachers and students via
technology. Students may be eligible to take courses not offered in Madison City Schools. ACCESS courses are available
at school during the school day, under the supervision of a trained facilitator. For further information, you may visit the
ACCESS web site at http://accessdl.state.al.us/ and select “Courses” to view courses currently available. This list may
change before the beginning of next school year. All requests for ACCESS courses must be made through your school
counselor. School administrators determine whether or not it is appropriate to register students for any course and will be
responsible for handling the registration process.

                                                                                 4]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Options Open is a Madison City Schools initiative designed to provide more flexibility for students. These opportunities will

allow students to build a unique schedule that matches their unique needs. The following are non-traditional class times

offered through Options Open:

             Course                             Meeting Times

             Zero Block        7:10am -8:00am

             Fifth Block       3:45pm – 5:00pm

             Online            Virtual Learning; max of 3 face-to-face meetings

             Blended           Mixture of face-to-face and online meetings

More information and registration materials pertaining to Options Open courses can be found in the registration packets

and online:

http://www.madisoncity.k12.al.us/?DivisionID=7842&DepartmentID=7748&SubDepartmentID=10293&ToggleSideNav=

             PROCEDURES RELATED TO GRADES AND CREDITS

Deficiencies
Only deficiencies will be reason for a schedule change. Once classes are balanced and sections are established, it is most
difficult to make a change without affecting the overall balance of teachers and class counts. For students who are not
successful during the regular school year and must repeat a class, summer school is suggested. You may also have the
option to participate in credit recovery.

Schedule “Changes” vs. Schedule “Corrections”
To provide the greatest probability for students to receive requested courses, a two week window was provided and then
deadline given to make schedule "changes". From there the master schedule was constructed and even teachers hired to
best ensure that what was requested would be received. Knowing that not every course request can be honored due to
conflicts in the student's schedule, the above procedure does provide the greatest potential for requests to be honored.
Therefore, at this time only schedule "corrections" will be made and only when approved by administration under
the following criteria: duplication of courses, courses are out of sequence, or Sports PE/Band to be entered due to
auditions

Partial Completion
Students will only earn credit for the total duration of a course. No credit will be given for partial completion.

Transfer Students
Students who transfer to Madison City Schools must complete all state mandated minimum graduation requirements and
any additional local graduation requirements. For mid-year or mid-semester transfer students from non-block scheduled
high schools, credits earned or coursework completed shall be correlated to the block-scheduled courses.

Transfer Grades
Letter grades transferred from previous schools will be placed on Madison City Schools’ Grade Point Average (GPA) scale
using the following guide:

     • Give weight to incoming Advanced Placement (or International Baccalaureate), and Dual Enrollment courses based
          upon the MCS weighted grading scale.

     • Give weight only to Honors/PreAP courses that are recognized as such by Madison City Schools since the Honors
          level is not nationally standardized.

     • Give MCS weight to Advanced Placement (or International Baccalaureate) courses even if the previous school did
          not weight AP since AP is a nationally standardized curriculum.

Early Completion
Students may complete required coursework early from Madison City Schools by meeting all requirements for an Alabama
High School Diploma as described in the Alabama Administrative Code 290-030-010-.6 (11) and meeting the requirements

                                                                                 5]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[of School Board Policy File: IHFB. Graduation is official and diploma awarded at the end of the regular school year. See a
counselor for details.

Graduation Participation
In order to participate in graduation ceremonies, a student must have met the requirements for a diploma or certificate from
Madison City Schools. See graduation requirements by Graduation Cohort year to review necessary coursework and
diploma/endorsement options for your graduating class.

Selection for Valedictorian and Salutatorian
The Valedictorian and Salutatorian are selected according to grade point average (GPA) rank at the end of the senior year.
To be eligible for Valedictorian and Salutatorian, a student must enroll prior to the end of the Madison City School’s first 9
week term of his/her senior year.

NCAA Requirements for College Athletes
Not all courses offered at Madison City Schools meet the NCAA eligibility requirements. It is the student’s responsibility to
review the requirements, schedule classes accordingly, and make sure the NCAA Initial-Eligibility Clearinghouse has the
documents to certify eligibility. Courses taken through the Credit Recovery program are not accepted by the NCAA
Eligibility Center. See Table of Contents for location of additional information.
* See pages 83-89 for more information.

Grading Scale        B 89-80  C 79-70  D 69-65             F 64-0
           A 100-90

Grade Point Average (GPA) Scale
Students electing to participate in rigorous academic courses such as Honors/PreAP, Advanced Placement is given
additional weight. The weighted Grade Point Average (GPA) will be recorded on the student’s report card, high school
official transcript, and included in the student’s overall GPA calculation. Credit bearing courses shall be awarded
according to the following scales:

                              Regular Honors/PreAP         AP
                                                           (6)
                              A (4)       (5)              (5)
                                                           (4)
                              B (3)       (4)              (3)
                                                           (0)
                              C (2)       (3)

                              D (1)       (2)

                              F (0)       (0)

Dual Enrollment
Madison City supports and encourages Dual Enrollment (DE) through agreements with Calhoun Community
College, Drake State Community and Technical College, and the University of Alabama in Huntsville. Students
who enroll in Dual Enrollment courses are responsible for verifying the high school credit and applicable GPA
calculation that will be received for the course from Madison City Schools. Students can verify the approved dual
enrollment course list (and corresponding grade point weights) referenced in the back of the curriculum catalog
or on the dual enrollment district webpage (https://tinyurl.com/hddpq6j). Courses included in the approved dual
enrollment list were requested by Madison City students. If a course is not included in the approved list, students
may submit a course review request through the following link: https://goo.gl/forms/H0wuJy520amph6h13.
Grades in DE courses will be awarded on the following scale as of June 1, 2017:

                                       Dual Enrollment

                     DE credit grades for courses with a prerequisite of All other DE credit grades shall be

                     AP shall be awarded on the AP scale.  awarded on the Regular scale.

A (6)                                                              (4)

B (5)                                                              (3)

C (4)                                                              (2)

D (3)                                                              (1)

F (0)                                                              (0)

All board polices are located on the Madison City web site at www.madisoncity.k12.al.us under Policies.

                                       6]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[COHORT

REQUIREMENTS

                               FOR
                        GRADUATION

                                               7]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Graduation Requirements by Cohort Group                                            2018-21
2017-2018 School Year

Beginning with Graduation Cohort 2017, there is only one diploma option, the Alabama High School Diploma. It was approved by the
Alabama State Board of Education in January 2013. This diploma option replaces all variations of the prior diploma. The purpose for the
change is to allow more flexibility for students in pursing their interest and to enable more balance through equivalent course offerings
preparing students for college AND careers. Pathways to graduation should be individualized based on the student’s interest, academic
ability, and career plans.

    Subject                               Requirements                             Credits

English Language                          English 9, 10, 11, and 12                     4
         Arts                    or any CTE/AP/IB equivalent courses.
                                                                                        4
   Mathematics                 Algebra 1, Geometry, and Algebra II/Trig
                                     or Algebra II, or their equivalent.                4

                         Additional course(s) to complete the four credits in           4
                    mathematics must be chosen from the Alabama Course of               1
                                                                                       0.5
                       Study: Mathematics or CTE/AP/IB equivalent courses               1
                                                                                   0.5 + 0.5
Science                  Biology and a Physical Science (i.e. Physical Science,         3
                                                Chemistry, Physics)                2.5 (4.5)
                                                                                    24 (26)
                    The third and fourth science credits may be used to meet both
                      the science and the CTE course requirement and must be
                         chosen from the Alabama Course of Study: Science or
                                        CTE/AP/IB equivalent courses.

   Social Studies   World History, US History x2, and Government/Economics
Physical Education                      or AP/IB equivalent courses
 Health Education
                                           LIFE (Personal Fitness)
                    One JROTC course may be used to meet this requirement.

                                                Health Education
                                     or Foundations of Health Science

       Career       Career Preparedness Course (to include topics of Career and
  Preparedness      Academic Planning, Computer Applications, Financial Literacy)

CTE and/or World                                             or
Language and/or            Career Preparedness A and Career Preparedness B

  Arts Education         Students choosing CTE*, Arts education, and/or World
                          language are encouraged to complete two courses in
      Electives
                                                       sequence.

                            State Requirement (Madison City Requirements)

                          Total Credits Required for Graduation (Madison City)

                    8]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[ALABAMA HIGH SCHOOL DIPLOMA
          SUBSTITUTE COURSES FOR STUDENTS WITH DISABILITIES

Areas of        Requirements                                                                       Credit
 Study

     English    English 9, 10, 11, and 12 or any AP or postsecondary equivalent option of           4
Language Arts   these courses.
                or *English Essentials 9, 10, 11, and 12                                            4
       Math     or **AAS English 9, 10, 11, and 12
                Algebra I, Geometry, and Algebra II with Trig or Algebra II or their equivalent.    4
    Science     Additional course(s) to complete the four credits in mathematics must be
                chosen from the Alabama Course of Study Mathematics or CTE/AP equivalent            4
Social Studies  courses.                                                                            1
                or *Algebraic Essentials A & B and Geometry Essentials A & B (students             0.5
    Physical    taking Algebraic Concepts in Grade 9 are not required to take Geometry B).          1
   Education    or **AAS Mathematics 9, 10, 11, 12                                                  3
                Biology and a Physical Science                                                     2.5
     Health     The third and fourth science credits may be used to meet both the science and
   Education    CTE requirement and must be chosen from the Alabama Course of Study:               24
                Science or CTE/AP equivalent courses.
     Career     or *Life Skills Science I, II, III and IV
Preparedness    or **AAS Science 9, 10, 11, and 12
                World History, US History X2, and Government/Economics or AP/Dual
  CTE and/or    Enrollment equivalent courses.
      World     or *World History for Living, US History for Living 10, US History for Living 11,
                and Economics for Living/US Government for Living
  Languages     or **AAS Social Studies 9, 10, 11 and 12
  and/or Arts   LIFE (Personal Fitness)
   Education    One JROTC credit may be used to meet this requirement.
                or Adapted Physical Education
    Electives
                Alabama Course of Study: Health Education
                or **AAS Pre-Vocational, AAS Vocational, AAS Community Based Instruction,
                and/or AAS Elective Course
                Career Preparedness Course(Career and Academic Planning, Computer
                Applications, Financial Literacy)
                or **AAS Life Skills
                Students choosing CTE, World Languages, and/or Arts Education are
                encouraged to complete two courses in sequence.
                or *two CTE courses and Workforce Essentials
                or **AAS Life Skills

                *Students earning core credit through the Essentials/Life Skills courses are
                required to take Cooperative Education Seminar/Work-Based Experience.
                **AAS Pre-Vocational, AAS Vocational, AAS Community Based Instruction,
                and/or AAS Elective Course.

                                                         Total Credits Required for Graduation

                9]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[MADISON CITY DIPLOMA ENDORSEMENTS
         GRADUATION COHORT 2017 AND BEYOND

Diploma                            Requirements

Alabama State Diploma              • See page 9 for Cohort requirements

Alabama State Diploma              • 2 World Language Credits
     • with Madison City Advanced  • Algebra II with Trig Credit
          Academic Endorsement     • 1 Advanced Placement Credit

Alabama State Diploma              • 2 World Language Credits
     • with Madison City Seal of   • Algebra II with Trig Credit
          Academic Distinction     • 3 Advanced Placement Credits

There are no state endorsements for Cohorts 2017 and beyond; however, there are two Madison City Endorsements:
    The Madison City Advanced Academic Endorsement and The Madison City Advanced Endorsement with Seal of
                                                                  Academic Distinction.

                                   FREQUENTLY ASKED QUESTIONS

How are grades reported?
Information NOW Parent Portal, Web Portal, Progress Reports, and Report Cards

Is there a specific supply list?
The individual teacher will provide a list of materials needed in addition to the routine school supplies on the first day of
class.

What classes are typically offered in Summer School?
Summer School is mainly for credit recovery and not credit advancement; however, Government and Economics online,
Freshmen Composition online, Health online, Career Prep A and B online, as well as Driver’s Ed are also offered.
Registration for Summer School will be posted on the individual school website and through School Messenger.

How do I know which courses are considered a Physical Science?
Physical Science, Chemistry, and Physics all meet the state requirements.

What courses meet the Health graduation requirement?
Health and Foundations of Health Science both meet the state requirement.

What courses meet the L.I.F.E. PE graduation requirement?
L.I.F.E. PE, Athletic L.I.F.E. PE, Color Guard, Marching Band, Percussion Marching Band, Percussion Indoor Drum Line,
and both Army and Air Force JROTC courses all satisfy the L.I.F.E. PE state requirement.

What is the difference in the Biomedical program and the Health Science program?
Both are the same in that through the completion of the courses, a student will have one regular weighted credit and three
honors weighted credits. Also, both are high interest programs and both provide wonderful experiences for students
interested in any health related field. However, the biomed courses consists of four tiered classes that may be entered in
either the 9th or 10th grade years and include research, diagnostics, medicine as a science, and treatment options. Health
Science may be entered as late as the junior or senior year and is focused more on patient care in diagnosis and treatment.
What Advanced Placement courses are appropriate for 9th and 10th grade students?

                                                                                10]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[AP World History and AP Human Geography are now offered at the 9th grade level for students who want to begin AP
coursework. AP World History, AP US History, AP Human Geography, AP European History, AP Psychology, and AP
Computer Science and AP Chemistry are appropriate courses for students at the 10th grade level.

How do I know if I could be successful in an Advanced Placement course?
We are currently using ASPIRE and PSAT student data to identify and inform students of academic areas for which they
have demonstrated the ability to be successful in AP coursework. Also, other factors such as previous grades, study habits,
personal work ethic, and interest all play a part in student success.

Do I have to take all Advanced Placement courses?
We encourage a student to push themselves to the highest academic rigor possible. It is recommended for students going
to college to take at least one AP course in their area of academic strength, personal interest and/or relevance to a planned
career path. AP courses mirror the rigor of college level classes.

Do I have to take Honors/PreAP or AP courses in order to earn an Alabama High School Diploma?
Students can meet the requirements of an Alabama High School Diploma without taking Honors/PreAP or AP courses.

What is the difference between regular and honors/PreAP?
Both regular and honors/PreAP courses will use the Alabama College and Career Ready grade level standards.
Honors/PreAP courses have additional added rigor. The same textbook will be used, yet different readings and materials
may supplement courses.

May students receive credit toward graduation for courses in the 8th grade?
Yes. Students may bring up to two credits of a math (Algebra I and Geometry), one credit of a World Language, and one
half credit of Career Prep A to the 9th grade (high school) transcript.**On September 30, 2013, the State Department of
Education approved Geometry as a course eighth grade course students could take for high school credit.

What determines my grade level?
Grade level assignment at the senior high level is determined by the number of years a student has attended at any senior
high school. For example, a student in his/her second year of high school will be labeled as a sophomore. Students who
have not met the requirements for graduation at the end of their fourth year of high school (senior year) will continue to be
labeled as seniors in subsequent school years until graduation requirements are obtained or the students are no longer
enrolled.

Why is it so difficult to change my class schedule? What’s the big deal?
Administrators and counselors spend an incredible amount of time building class schedules that reflect the students’ goals
and interests, fairly distributing students among similar classes, and placing courses at times in the day when the most
students can take requested classes. Once classes are balanced and sections are established, it is most difficult to make a
change without affecting the overall balance of teachers and class counts. Teachers are hired and textbooks are purchased
based on the course enrollment as projected in the spring thereby limiting availability of classes and textbooks.

What happens if I fail a class?
For students who are not successful during the regular school year and must repeat a class, summer school may be a
necessity. You may also have the option of participation in the Credit Recovery program or re-enroll the following semester.

                                                                                11]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[2017

2018

         COURSE
      DESCRIPTIONS

      12]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[THE ACADEMIES OF CAREER TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION

                                          Course                               Credit  Fee

                                 CAREER PREPAREDNESS                                   $30
                                                                                       $30
400025    Career Preparedness (JCHS)                                           1.0     $30
                                                                               1.0     $70
802200am Career Preparedness (JCHS – Online)                                   0.5     $20
                                                                               0.5     $30
400026    Career Preparedness A                                                0.5     $20
                                                                                       $70
 400027   Career Preparedness B                                                1.0     $20
802200ae  Career Preparedness B (JCHS – Online)                                1.0     TBD
                                                                               1.0
                                 MEDICAL ACADEMY                               2.0     $20
                                                                                       $20
Biomedical Sciences (PLTW four course sequence)                                1.0     $20
                                                                               1.0     $20
490042    Principles of the Biomedical Sciences-PLTW                           1.0     $20
                                                                               2.0     $20
490043    Human Body Systems-PLTW (Honors)                                     1.0
490044    Medical Interventions-PLTW (Honors)                                          $20
                                                                               1.0     $20
490001    Biomedical Innovations-PLTW (Honors)                                         $20
                                                                               1.0     $20
Health Science (three course sequence*)                                                $20
                                                                                       $20
490024    Orientation to Health Science                                                $20
                                                                                       $20
490007    Foundations of Health Science*
          (a substitute for the state required health credit)                          $20
                                                                                       $20
490015    Human Body Structures & Functions (Honors)*

490014    Health Science Internship* (2 blocks / Honors)
490022    Introduction to Pharmacy (Honors)

Emergency Medical Technician

802111    Emergency Medical Technician (Dual Enrollment)

                                 ENGINEERING ACADEMY

Project Lead the Way (three course sequence*)

560015    Introduction to Engineering Design*

560016    Principles of Engineering (Honors)*                                  1.0

560018    Aerospace Engineering (Honors) JCHS                                  1.0

560020    Civil Engineering and Architecture (Honors) BJHS                     1.0

560014    Engineering Internship: Research and Design with Senior Career       2.0
          Pathway Project (Honors)*

560021    Computer Integrated Manufacturing – PLTW (Honors)                    1.0

                                 BUSINESS ACADEMY

Business Management and Administration

450006    Business Technology Applications (BTA)                               1.0

450031    Advanced Business Tech Applications (Honors)                         1.0

410016    Multimedia Design                                                    1.0

410017    Multimedia Publications (BJHS)                                       1.0

450032    Senior Career Pathway Project-Business, Management & Administration  1.0

Marketing Sales and Service

450006    Business Technology Applications (BTA)                               1.0

550011    Marketing Principles                                                 1.0

550021    Sales and Promotion Planning (Sports Marketing)                      1.0

550022    Senior Career Pathway Project-Marketing Sales and Service            1.0

          ARTS, A/V TECHNOLOGY, AND COMMUNICATIONS ACADEMY

Technology and Broadcasting JCHS

440017    Introduction to Television Production                                1.0

440020    Television Production, Photography, and Editing                      1.0

                                                 13]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Course                                 Credit  Fee

440021   Advanced Television Production (JETSPress)                               1.0  $20
                                                                                  1.0  $20
440054   Senior Career Pathway Project-Arts, A/V Tech & Communications

                                HUMAN SERVICES ACADEMY

Fashion

510004   Family and Consumer Science                                           1.0 $20
                                                                               1.0 $30
510041   Fashion                                                               1.0 $30
                                                                               1.0 $30
510044   Fashion Design
                                                                               1.0 $20
410015   Fashion Merchandising                                                 1.0 $30
                                                                               1.0 $35
Family Studies and Community Service                                           1.0 $30

510004   Family and Consumer Science                                           1.0 $15
                                                                               1.0 $20
510041   Fashion                                                               1.0 $20
                                                                               2.0 $20
510011   Food and Nutrition
                                                                               1.0 $60
510021   Child Development                                                     1.0 $70
                                                                               1.0 $70
Education and Training

460009   Education and Training

460011   Teaching I

460012   Teaching II

460015   Education and Training Internship

Hospitality and Tourism – BJHS

500011   Hospitality & Tourism

500012   Culinary Arts I

500013   Culinary Arts II

                             COMPUTER SCIENCE ACADEMY

Programming and Software Development

520015   Software Development (C Programming)                                  1.0 $20

520013   Database Design (C ++ Programming) (Honors)                           1.0 $20

520007   AP Computer Science A                                                 1.0     $20 + AP
                                                                                       Exam Fee

260007   AP Computer Science Principles                                        1.0 AP Exam Fee

520037   Senior Career Pathway Project-Information Technology                  1.0 $20
         (Independent Comp. Research)

Informational Security (Cybersecurity)

925689   IT Fundamentals                                                       1.0 $20
                                                                               1.0 $20
520038   Foundations of Informational Security (Cybersecurity I)               1.0 $20

520039   Principles of Informational Security (Cybersecurity II)

                           BUILDING CONSTRUCTION ACADEMY

Building Science

430004   Architecture, Construction, and Manufacturing                         1.0 $30
                                                                               1.0 $30
412102   NCCER Construction Site Preparation & Foundation                      1.0 $30

412101   NCCER Building Construction I - Construction Framing                  1.0 $30

412103   NCCER Building Construction II - Construction Finishing and Interior  1.0 $30
         Systems                                                               1.0 $30

420057   Landscape Design and Management                                       1.0 $25
                                                                               1.0 $25
430129   Senior Career Pathway Project-Construction                            1.0 $25
                                                                               1.0 $25
                             AIR FORCE JUNIOR ROTC / BJHS                      1.0 $25
                                                                               1.0 $25
480001   AFJROTC: Leadership and Aviation History- Part I                      1.0 $25

480022/480025 AFJROTC: Leadership and Aviation History – Part II

480031   AFROTC: Leadership and Cultural Studies – Part I

480021/480027 AFROTC: Leadership and Cultural Studies – Part II

480002   AFROTC: Leadership and Science of Flight – Part I

480023/480026 AFJROTC: Leadership and Science of Flight – Part II

480029   AFJROTC: Leadership and Exploration of Space

                                            14]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Course                                        Credit  Fee

480030  AFJROTC: Leadership and Management of the Cadet Corps and  1.0     $25
        Financial Education                                                $25
480032  AFROTC: Leadership and Survival                            1.0
                                                                           $25
480041                            ARMY JUNIOR ROTC / JCHS          1.0     $25
480042                                                             1.0     $25
480043  Army JROTC Leadership Education and Training I (LETI)      1.0     $25
480044  Army JROTC Leadership and Training II (LETII)              1.0
        Army JROTC Leadership and Training III (LETIII)                    $20
400122  Army JROTC Leadership and Training IV (LETIV)              1.0     $20
400133                                                             1.0     $20
400144            WORK-BASED LEARNING *Formerly Known as Co-Op     1.0     $20
400212                                                             1.0
        Work-Based Experience-First Credit
        Work-Based Experience-Second Credit
        Work-Based Experience-Third Credit
        Work-Based Experience-Fourth Credit

CAREER PREPAREDNESS

                Career Preparedness
18 weeks/1 credit
A full credit course that is taught in grades 9-12. The course prepares students with knowledge and skills in the areas of
career development and academic planning, computer skills application, and financial literacy. The required 20-hour online
experience can be met by successful completion of this course.

                        *This course is available online through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for more
                        information.

            Career Preparedness A
9 weeks/0.5 credit
A one-half credit course that is taught in grades 9-12. The course prepares students with knowledge and skills in the areas
of career development and academic planning and computer skill application. This course is a prerequisite to Career
Preparedness-B. The required 20-hour online experience can be met by successfully completing both Career
Preparedness A and Career Preparedness B.

                        *This course is available online through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for more
                        information.

Career Preparedness B
9 weeks/0.5 credit
A one-half credit course that is taught in grades 9-12. The course prepares students with knowledge and skills in the areas
of career development and academic planning and financial literacy. The prerequisite for this course is Career
Preparedness-A. The required 20-hour online experience can be met by successful completion of both Career
Preparedness A and Career Preparedness B.

                        *This course is available online through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for more
                        information.

                     15]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[MEDICAL ACADEMY

BIOMEDICAL SCIENCE – A four course sequence*

Principles of the Biomedical Sciences*
18 weeks/1 credit
In the introductory course of the PLTW Biomedical Science program, students explore concepts of biology and medicine to
determine factors that led to the death of a fictional person. While investigating the case, students examine
autopsy reports, investigate medical history, and explore medical treatments that might have prolonged the person’s life.
The activities and projects introduce students to human physiology, basic biology, medicine, and research processes
while allowing them to design their own experiments to solve problems.

Human Body Systems*
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Principles of the Biomedical Sciences, Chemistry
Honors Credit Awarded
Students examine the interactions of human body systems as they explore identity, power, movement, protection, and
homeostasis. Exploring science in action, students build organs and tissues on a skeletal Maniken®; use data acquisition
software to monitor body functions such as muscle movement, reflex and voluntary action, and respiration; and take on the
roles of biomedical professionals to solve real-world medical cases.

Medical Interventions*
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Human Body Systems
Honors Credit Awarded

Students follow the life of a fictitious family as they investigate how to prevent, diagnose, and treat disease. Students
explore how to detect and fight infection; screen and evaluate the code in human DNA; evaluate cancer treatment options;
and prevail when the organs of the body begin to fail. Through real-world cases, students are exposed to a range of
interventions related to immunology, surgery, genetics, pharmacology, medical devices, and diagnostics.

Biomedical Innovations*
18 weeks/2 credits/ double block
Prerequisite: Medical Interventions
Honors Credit Awarded
In the final course of the PLTW Biomedical Science sequence, students build on the knowledge and skills gained from
previous courses to design innovative solutions for the most pressing health challenges of the 21st century. Students
address topics ranging from public health and biomedical engineering to clinical medicine and physiology. They have the
opportunity to work on an independent design project with a mentor or advisor from a university, medical facility, or research
institution. As a part of the course students complete a clinical internship at local health care facilities which provides
students with the knowledge and skills necessary for becoming a health care worker, or assisting with research in a
laboratory setting or for preparing students for postsecondary health care education programs. Throughout the course,
students are expected to present their work to an audience of professionals. Discipline and attendance will be considered
for enrollment in the course. Recommendation: C average in Biomedical Science course sequence
*Some clinical sites require students over the age of 17 to have a background check. Therefore, students over 17
years of age should be prepared to have a background check completed and pay the fee associated with the
background check. Students may see their teacher(s) for more information on having the background check
completed.

                                                                                16]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[HEALTH SCIENCE— A three course sequence*

Orientation to Health Science
18 weeks/1 credit
Orientation to Health Science is a one credit course to assist students in making informed decisions regarding their college
and career goals. Students will be given the opportunity to apply knowledge and skills related to the Health Science cluster.
The course also includes information concerning the practices for promoting health, wellness, and disease prevention.
Instruction and learning activities are provided in a laboratory setting using hands-on experiences with the equipment,
materials and technology appropriate to the course content and in accordance with current practices.

Foundations of Health Science*
18 weeks/1 credit
Foundations of Health Science introduces students to a wide range of health careers. Integrated academics combined with
health care knowledge and skills provide the framework for a strong healthcare delivery system in the twenty-first century.
This course is a prerequisite for Health Science Internship and the Emergency Medical Technician (EMT) course. It is
recommended for all students who want to prepare for further study in an array of health-related fields at the postsecondary
level. This course is a substitute for the state required health credit. It is recommended that students take this class
their sophomore or junior year if planning to take senior Health Science Internship.

Human Body Structures and Functions (Human Anatomy & Physiology)*
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Biology or concurrent Chemistry
Honors Credit Awarded
Prepares students for biomedical, nursing, and other health-related careers, and is a prerequisite for Health Science
Internship: organized to follow a logical sequence of the eleven systems of the human body with emphasis on diseases and
disorders. Laboratory dissection includes anatomical study of a mammal. Discipline and attendance will be considered.

Health Science Internship* (12th grade)
18 weeks/2 credits double-block
Prerequisites: Foundations of Health Science and Human Body Structures and Functions (Human A&P)
Honors Credit Awarded
Health Science Internship provides students with the knowledge and skills necessary for becoming a health care worker or
for preparing students for postsecondary health care educational programs. Theory and laboratory components comprise at
least ten percent of the course. Health Science Internship is designed to be completed in a hospital, extended care facility,
rehabilitation center, medical office, imaging center, laboratory, or other health care facilities. Discipline and attendance will
be considered.
*Some clinical sites require students over the age of 17 to have a background check. Therefore, students over 17
years of age should be prepared to have a background check completed and pay the fee associated with the
background check. Students may see their teacher(s) for more information on having the background check
completed.

Introduction to Pharmacy
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisites: Foundations of Health Science and Human Body Structures and Functions (Human A&P) OR
Principles of Biomedical Sciences and Human Body Systems
Honors Credit Awarded
A one-credit course that introduces students to the pharmaceutical profession. The course covers content related to the
history of medicine, mathematics, technology, legal issues, and technical skills. Upon completion of this course, students
will be eligible to take the national pharmacy technician exam; a high school diploma is required to sit for this exam.
Students are responsible for the cost of the certification exam.

                                                                                17]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[ENGINEERING

PROJECT LEAD THE WAY –A three course sequence*

Introduction to Engineering Design* (IED)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra I
Corequisite: Geometry
Designed for 9th or 10th grade students, the major focus of IED is the design process and its application. Through hands-on
projects, students apply engineering standards and document their work. Students use industry standard 3D modeling
software to help them design solutions to solve proposed problems, document their work using an engineer’s notebook, and
communicate solutions to peers and members of the professional community.

Principles of Engineering* (POE)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Introduction to Engineering Design Corequisite: Algebra II with Trigonometry
Honors Credit Awarded
Designed for 10th or 11th grade students, this survey course exposes students to major concepts they’ll encounter in a post-
secondary engineering course of study. Topics include mechanisms, energy, statics, materials, and kinematics. They
develop problem-solving skills and apply their knowledge of research and design to create solutions to various challenges,
document their work and communication solutions.

                Aerospace Engineering
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Principles of Engineering
Honors Credit Awarded
A one-credit course that provides opportunities for students to develop projects with NASA-aerodynamics, astronautics,
space-life sciences, and systems engineering.

            Civil Engineering and Architecture
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Principles of Engineering OR NCCER Construction Finishing and Interior Systems
Honors Credit Awarded
A one-credit course that provides opportunities for students to learn important aspects of building and site design and
development. They apply math, science, and standard engineering practices to design both residential and commercial
projects and document their work using 3D architecture design software.

Engineering Internship: Research and Design with Senior Career Pathway Project*
18 weeks/2 credits double-block
Prerequisite: Principles of Engineering
Honors Credit Awarded
The pinnacle of the Engineering Academy presents students with the opportunity to apply the knowledge and skills they
have obtained in the previous two engineering classes. This senior-level class will solidify the student's understanding of
engineering principles as they leave the campus to intern at local engineering companies. Class time will be spent
polishing communication skills and participating in a senior project and report. Students should provide their own
transportation to and from job sites.

                                                                                18]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Computer Integrated Manufacturing (PLTW)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Introduction to Engineering Design
Honors Credit Awarded
Manufactured items are part of everyday life, yet most students have not been introduced to the high tech, innovative
nature of modern manufacturing. This course illuminates the opportunities related to understanding manufacturing. At the
same time, it teaches students about manufacturing processes, product design, robotics, and automation. Students can
earn a virtual manufacturing badge recognized by the National Manufacturing Badge system.

                                          BUSINESS ACADEMY

BUSINESS MANAGEMENT AND ADMINISTRATION

Business Technology Applications (BTA)
18 weeks/1 credit
Course meets the state requirement for computer proficiency for the State of Alabama. Students master skills in word
processing, database, spreadsheet, presentation, and Internet use. A major emphasis is placed on preparing students for
Microsoft Office Specialist (MOS) certification after mastering each MS Office application. (MOS Certifications offered: Word
2013 and PowerPoint 2013)This course also provides college credit at any community college in the state of Alabama.
Please see Alabama Community College System State-Wide Articulation Agreements for details.

Advanced Business Technology Applications
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: BTA
Honors Credit Awarded
This honors business course refines concepts learned in Business Technology Applications. Microsoft Office skills and
projects are integrated throughout the course. A major emphasis is placed on preparing students for Microsoft Office
Specialist (MOS) certification after mastering each MS Office application. (MOS Certifications offered: Excel 2013 and
Access 2013 or other MS Office application). This course also provides college credit at any community college in the state
of Alabama. Please see Alabama Community College System State-Wide Articulation Agreement.

Multimedia Design
18 weeks/1 credit
Course designed to provide students with hands-on skills involving graphic design, digital photography, Web publishing, and
digital video production. Students use various hardware peripherals and software for completing documents. Students
contribute material for school websites and their own personal portfolios. FBLA is the Career Technical organization that is
an integral, co-curricular component of the course. A prerequisite of Creative Writing is recommended but not required. A
major emphasis is placed on preparing students for optional credentialing through Adobe certification available upon
completion of this course.

            Multimedia Publications
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Creative Writing I OR Multimedia Design
Course designed to further the hands-on skills of graphic design, digital photography, Web publishing, and digital video
production. Students use various hardware peripherals and software for completing documents. Students contribute
material for print publications, school websites, and their own personal portfolios. FBLA is the Career Technical
organization that is an integral, co-curricular component of the course. A major emphasis is placed on preparing students
for optional credentialing through Adobe (to include InDesign, Illustrator, Flash, Dreamweaver, and Photoshop)
certification available upon completion of this course.

                                                                                19]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Senior Career Pathway Project-Business, Management & Administration
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Multimedia Publications (BJHS) or Multimedia Design (JCHS)
A one-credit course designed for students who have completed a minimum of two career and technical education courses
to select an area of interest; engage in in-depth exploration of the area; employ problem-solving, decision-making, and
independent learning skills; and present a culminating pathway project before a selected audience.

MARKETING SALES AND SERVICE

Business Technology Applications (BTA)
18 weeks/1 credit
Course meets the state requirement for computer proficiency for the State of Alabama. Students master skills in word
processing, database, spreadsheet, presentation, and Internet use. A major emphasis is placed on preparing students for
Microsoft Office Specialist (MOS) certification after mastering each MS Office application. (MOS Certifications offered: Word
2013 and PowerPoint 2013)This course also provides college credit at any community college in the state of Alabama.
Please see Alabama Community College System State-Wide Articulation Agreements for details.

Marketing Principles
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: BTA or Career Preparedness A AND concurrent Career Preparedness B
Course provides students with an overview of in-depth marketing concepts. Students develop a foundational knowledge of
marketing and its functions, including marketing information management, pricing, product and service management,
entrepreneurship, promotion and selling. Students examine the need for sales and marketing strategies, practice customer
relationship skills, ethics, technology and communication in the workplace. DECA is the Career/Technical organization that
is an integral, co-curricular component of the course.

Sales and Promotion Planning (Sports Marketing)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: BTA or Career Preparedness A AND concurrent Career Preparedness B
Students will develop skills in advertising, publicity, special events, visual merchandising, displays, promotional campaigns,
and advertisements to aid in promotional planning. The skills will all be taught with
an emphasis on professional sports teams. Partnerships with local teams will be utilized. DECA is the Career/Technical
organization that is an integral, co-curricular component of the course.

                ARTS, A/V TECHNOLOGY, COMMUNICATIONS ACADEMY

                 TECHNOLOGY AND BROADCASTING—A three course sequence.*

Introduction to Television Production*
18 weeks/1 credit
A one-credit course that provides students with knowledge of television production skills and operations. Students
participate in classroom and laboratory experiences in television performance, production, and operations.

Television Production—Photography and Editing*
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Introduction to Television Production
A one-credit course that provides students with a variety of real-world learning opportunities through laboratory
experiences in photography and editing for television productions. The prerequisite for this course is Introduction to
Television Production.

                                                                                20]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Advanced Television Production (JETSPress)*
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Television Production—Photography and Editing
A one-credit course that provides students with opportunities to create and market video productions. The prerequisite
courses for Advanced Television Production are Introduction to Television Production and a minimum of one additional
Television Production course which includes Television Production—Writing, Producing, and Performing; Television
Production—Studio Operations; or Television Production—Photography and Editing.

Senior Career Pathway Project Arts, A/V Technology, and Communications
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Television Production—Photography and Editing, Advanced Television Production
A one-credit course designed for students who have completed a minimum of two career and technical education courses
to select an area of interest; engage in in-depth exploration of the area; employ problem-solving, decision-making, and
independent learning skills; and present a culminating pathway project before a selected audience.

                                    HUMAN SERVICES ACADEMY

FASHION

Family and Consumer Science
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is the introductory course to the Human Services Academy. This course will allow students to explore nutrition
and cooking, communication, family relationships, interior design, fashion and sewing techniques and much more. As an
overview course, this allows students to explore all the pathways offered in FACS. It is recommended that students take
this course their freshman or sophomore year if planning to take Fashion Merchandising.

Fashion
18 weeks/1 credit
This foundation course provides students with an insight to the knowledge and skills required for a career in the apparel,
textile, and fashion industries. The student will become familiar with fashion terminology, study famous fashion designers,
and apply construction and design techniques in lab settings. The student will become familiar with all types of hand and
machine sewing and utilize current technology in the sewing lab. Additional costs will be required as special projects are
constructed during the course. *This course may also be taken in the Family Studies and Community Service course
sequence.

Fashion Design
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Fashion
This class will provide the student with advanced knowledge and skills used in the Fashion Design field. Concepts learned
in lab (HANDS ON CLASS) include the following: designing textiles; developing a clothing line; marketing and promoting
designs; analyzing the different promotional techniques; planning a fashion show; preparing a college-ready design portfolio;
operating tools and equipment used in design studio. Additional costs will be required as special textile projects are
constructed during the course. Good attendance is required for success in this highly lab-based course.

Fashion Merchandising
18 weeks/ 1 credit
Prerequisite: Fashion Design
This course is designed for students who are interested in acquiring knowledge and skills in the Fashion Design, Textiles,
and Retail Industries. Students discover ways to express themselves in art and fashion while becoming aware of how art
relates to the fashion and textile industries. This studio lab-based curriculum includes the study of the elements/principles
of design; use of various media/techniques; fashion illustration; sewing and construction techniques; portfolio
development; analyzing licensing practices, and the study of trade associations and careers in the fashion/textile
industries. Good attendance is required for success in this highly lab based course.

                                                                                21]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[FAMILY STUDIES AND COMMUNITY SERVICE

Family and Consumer Science
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is the introductory course to the Human Services Academy. This course will allow students to explore nutrition
and cooking, communication, family relationships, interior design, fashion and sewing techniques and much more. As an
overview course, this allows students to explore all the pathways offered in FACS

Fashion
18 weeks/1 credit
This foundation course provides students with an insight to the knowledge and skills required for a career in the apparel,
textile, and fashion industries. The student will become familiar with fashion terminology, study famous fashion designers,
and apply construction and design techniques in lab settings. The student will become familiar with all types of hand and
machine sewing and utilize current technology in the sewing lab. Additional costs will be required as special projects are
constructed during the course. Good attendance is required for success in this highly lab based course. *This course may
also be taken in the Fashion course sequence.

Food and Nutrition
18 week/1 credit
Prerequisite: Family and Consumer Science
Topics include the impact of daily nutrition and wellness practices on long-term health and wellness; physical, social, and
psychological aspects of healthy nutrition and wellness choices; selection and preparation of nutritious meals and snacks
based on USDA Dietary Guidelines, including the Food Guide Pyramid; safety, sanitation, storage, and recycling processes
and issues associated with nutrition and wellness; impacts of science and technology on nutrition and wellness issues; and
nutrition and wellness career paths.

Child Development
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Family and Consumer Science
Students will explore the development of children from birth to 12 years and observe children at different stages of
development. Students will take home a “Baby Think It Over” Infant Simulator and will study factors that affect children like
health issues, education, and abuse. Students will analyze career options in the area of Child Development.

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

Education and Training
18 weeks/1 credit
This foundation course is designed for students who are interested in pursuing careers in education. Course content includes
the organizational structure of education, careers, the role of the teacher, characteristics of effective teachers,
communication skills, the teaching and learning processes, learning styles, research, characteristics of positive classroom
environments, human growth and development, curriculum development, student characteristics, teaching techniques,
learning activities, educational initiatives, technology, and careers. Observational experiences are a required component of
this course.

Teaching I
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Education and Training
The course includes content that helps students implement the teaching and learning processes. Major topics included in
this course are funding sources, budget preparations, legal aspects, research, teaching and learning theories, curriculum
development, positive learning environments, creative teaching techniques, appropriate learning activities, instructional
resources, community resources and services, scope and sequence charts, course outlines, lesson plans, testing, grading,
developing partnerships, technology, and careers. School-based laboratory experiences are essential for students to
develop skills in teaching. Observational experiences are a required component of this course.

                                                                                22]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Teaching II
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Teaching I
This course provides students with advanced knowledge and utilization of skills in the field of education and is an extension
of Teaching 1; embedded service learning through job shadowing in areas schools will be an integral component of this
course.

Education and Training Internship
18 weeks / 2 credits / double block
Prerequisite: Teaching II
This course is designed for students interested in pursuing an internship experience in an educational field. Students who
have completed Teaching II are eligible to enroll in the Education and Training Internship.

           HOSPITALITY AND TOURISM

Hospitality & Tourism
18 weeks /1 credit
This course is the prerequisite for all courses included in the Hospitality and Tourism cluster. Major topics include
introduction to hospitality and tourism, recreation, travel and tourism, lodging, restaurants and food and beverage services,
safety and sanitation, customer relations, and quality services. The required school-based laboratory for the Hospitality
and Tourism cluster is a commercial food service kitchen with a food serving and dining area. School-based laboratory
experiences are essential for students to develop skills in the hospitality and tourism industry.

Culinary I
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Hospitality and Tourism
Students learn basic food production, management, and service activities in both the back- and- front-of-the- house.
Emphasis is placed on sanitation, safety, and basic food preparation. Skills in mathematics, science, and communication
are reinforced in this course. The required school-based laboratory for Culinary 1 is a commercial food service kitchen with
a food serving and dining area. School-based laboratory experiences are essential for students to develop skills in the
hospitality and tourism industry.

Culinary II
18 week /1 credit
Prerequisite: Culinary 1 and Teacher Approval
Culinary 2 provides advanced experiences in food production, management, and service. Topics include food service
operations, advanced food production, and professionalism. Skills in mathematics, communication, creative thinking, and
entrepreneurship are reinforced in this course. The required school-based laboratory for Culinary 2 is a commercial food
service kitchen with a food serving and dining area. School-based laboratory experiences are essential for students to
develop skills in the hospitality and tourism industry.

                                  COMPUTER SCIENCE ACADEMY

PROGRAMMING AND SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

Software Development/C Programming
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra I
B or higher average in Algebra 1 is strongly recommended
After being introduced to basic computer terminology, students will learn to program in C and will acquire a thorough
understanding of variables, loop techniques, functions, and procedures. Good programming techniques will also be
stressed. It will be expected that students have solid basic math skills, keyboarding skills, and experience using several
computer applications.
Database Design III / C++ Programming

                                                                                23]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[18 weeks/1 credit
Honors Credit Awarded
Prerequisite: Algebra II with Trigonometry and Software Development (C Programming)
B or higher average in Software Development (C Programming) is strongly recommended
Students will learn the fundamentals of C++ and object-oriented programming languages. Good programming techniques
will also be stressed.

Advanced Placement Computer Science A
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Database Design III (C++ Programming)
B or higher average in Database Design III (C++ Programming) is strongly recommended
This advanced placement course is accelerated in rigor and pace. Students will cover an in-depth study of JAVA and
object-oriented programming languages. Participation in the national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor
of this course

Advanced Placement Computer Science Principles
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Geometry
College-level advanced course following the curriculum established by the College Board Advanced Placement (AP)
program for computer science. This course is designed to introduce students to the seven central ideas of computing and
computer science. The content is focused on creativity, abstraction, algorithms, programming, big data,
Internet/networking, and societal impact. Throughout the course there will be a significant amount of research, writing, and
programming. This course is NOT the prerequisite for any of the other computer science courses. Participation in the
national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course. The AP exam consists of two parts –
multiple choice exam and a portfolio.

Senior Career Pathway Project – Information Technology (Independent Computer Research)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Database Design III (C++ Programming) AND Teacher Approval
Corequisite (if not already taken): AP Computer Science A
Honors Credit Awarded
Each student will complete a research project on an independent study basis and will also assist as an aide in the C
and/or C++ Programming class. This course will also provide opportunities for job shadowing and internships with local
companies.

INFORMATIONAL SECURITY

IT Fundamentals
18 weeks/1 credit
This is an introductory level course that covers the fundamentals of software, hardware, security, and networking, as well
as basic IT skills such as workstation set-up, operating system navigation, simple support services, backup protocols, and
safety. Upon completion of the course, students will understand the essential functions of IT professionals and be better
positioned to make decisions about a career in information technology.

Foundations of Informational Security (Cybersecurity I)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: IT Fundamentals
In this hands-on course, students explore Microsoft and Linux operating systems, identify and eliminate security
vulnerabilities, and gain confidence to perform system administration tasks. They are exposed to the hacker culture and
learn to differentiate between legal and illegal computer activity. Through a series of exercises they have an opportunity to
manage passwords and test their strength, monitor network activity, and exploit system weaknesses. Finally, they meet and
work with security professionals gain a better understanding of how cyber security could fit into their career plans.

                                                                                24]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Principles of Informational Security (Cybersecurity II)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Foundations of Informational Security (Cybersecurity I)
A one-credit course that introduces students to computer network systems that are most commonly the focus of attack.
Students will build and configure the common elements found on the Internet to include database servers, web servers,
and web application servers. Students will be introduced to remote access terminal shells which will be vital toward
penetration testing and attack vectors. Prerequisite: Foundations of Informational Security

                              BUILDING CONSTRUCTION ACADEMY

BUILDING SCIENCE

Architecture, Construction, and Manufacturing18 weeks/1 credit
This course introduces students to core knowledge and skills in the areas of design, preconstruction, construction,
maintenance, operations, and installation and repair which are foundational to courses related to careers in the
architecture and construction and manufacturing industries.

NCCER Construction Site Preparation and Foundations
18 weeks/1 credit
Designed to facilitate students’ understanding of the first phases of construction and include types of structures and their
uses.

NCCER Construction Framing
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Construction Site Prep and Foundations
Provides students with an understanding of the framing phase of a structure, including framing components. Topics include
career opportunities, safety, lumber, material estimation, floor systems, wall framing, ceiling framing, stair construction, roof
framing, and roof materials in various structures.

NCCER Construction Finishing and Interior Systems
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Construction Framing
Provides instruction on the exterior and interior finishing of a structure. Students will make a project out of woodworking
tools and the following topics will be taught: plumbing, electricity, drywall, insulation and cabinet making. *Students who
successfully complete the Architecture and Building Construction Academy three course sequence (Construction Framing,
Construction Site Preparation and Foundations, and Construction Finishing and Interior Systems) are eligible to take the
Civil Engineering and Architecture course.

Landscape Design and Management
18 weeks/1 credit
This course allows students to become more knowledgeable about and appreciative of landscape design and management.
Students receive instruction that allows them to participate in hands-on activities in the areas of landscape drawing and
design; landscape plant identification, classification, and selection; landscape growth and the environment; landscape
establishment and management; landscape tools and equipment; landscape drainage and irrigation; insects, diseases, and
weeds; landscape features; residential turf grass management; interior plantscapes; xeriscaping; business management;
and environmental issues.

Senior Career Pathway Project: Building and Construction
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Successful completion of at least one NCCER course
A one-credit course designed for students who have completed a minimum of two career and technical education courses
to select an area of interest; engage in in-depth exploration of the area; employ problem-solving, decision-making, and
independent learning skills; and present a culminating pathway project before a selected audience.

                                                                                25]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[JROTC ACADEMY

           AIR FORCE JUNIOR ROTC

AFJROTC creates tomorrow’s leaders and develops citizens of character. It is NOT a military recruitment program; students
incur NO military service obligation. Students learn and demonstrate patriotism, citizenship, personal obligation to contribute
to individual/community/national goals, leadership and life skills. Physical fitness is emphasized in each course. Military drill
is used in every course to teach leadership & discipline and to give students opportunities to practice leadership skills. The
courses include an emphasis on aerospace science as an important component of the US military and industry. Students
may participate in many organized activities outside of class (field trips, leadership schools, marksmanship competitions,
drill meets, parades, military balls, model rocketry, and community service projects.) Students who have not taken
AFJROTC before begin the program by completing the first two introduction courses; the remaining courses may be taken
in any sequence.

For each AFJROTC courses:
1. Students are required to properly wear the AFJROTC uniform one day a week and on special occasions.
2. Students must sign an agreement to adhere to AFJROTC grooming standards for correct uniform wear (including proper
hair length and style, and no unnatural hair coloring).
3. A fee is required.
In addition to receiving a Career Tech elective credit for each course completed, completing one AFJROTC course fulfills
the L.I.F.E. physical education requirement for the Alabama HS diploma. Completing the two introductory AFJROTC
courses fulfills the Career Prep requirement for the Alabama HS diploma.

Introduction to AFJROTC:
480001 AFJROTC: Leadership and Aviation History – Part 1 (18 Weeks/ 1 credit)
Students learn the historical development of flight and the role of the military in history, from ancient legends through the
Korean War. Students are also taught career readiness and how to prepare for life after high school in the high-tech, globally
oriented, and diverse workplace of the 21st century. Students participate in military drill and ceremonies execution and
performance, and learn how drill helps the individual, builds the team, and develops leaders. Students participate in a
physical training program to reach fitness goals and encourage life-long wellness. **Upon successful completion of this
course, students may earn credit for the graduation requirement of Career Prep A. [Every Fall Semester]

480022/480025 AFJROTC: Leadership and Aviation History – Part 2 (18 Weeks/ 1 credit)
Students learn the historical development of flight and the role of the military in history, from the Korean War through the
present. Students also learn life skills, such as financial planning and choosing a career/college. Students participate in
military drill and ceremonies execution and performance, and learn how drill helps the individual, builds the team, and
develops leaders. Students participate in a physical training program to reach fitness goals and encourage life-long wellness.
**Upon successful completion of this course, students may earn credit for the graduation requirement of Career
Prep B. [Every Spring Semester]

Advanced AFJROTC:
480002 AFJROTC: Leadership and Science of Flight – Part I (18 Weeks/ 1 credit)
Students learn about the aerospace environment and the human requirements of flight. Students will also learn effective
communication and increased awareness of self and others. Students participate in military drill and ceremonies execution
and performance, and learn how drill helps the individual, builds the team, and develops leaders. Students participate in a
physical training program to reach fitness goals and encourage life-long wellness. [Fall 2017]

480023/480026 AFJROTC: Leadership and Science of Flight – Part II (18 Weeks/ 1 credit)
Students learn about principles of aircraft flight, and principles of navigation. Students will also learn values of personal
integrity, service, & excellence and improve leadership techniques. Students participate in military drill and ceremonies
execution and performance, and learn how drill helps the individual, builds the team, and develops leaders. Students
participate in a physical training program to reach fitness goals and encourage life-long wellness. [Spring 2018]

                                                                                26]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[480021/480027 AFJROTC: Leadership and Cultural Studies – Part II (18 Weeks/ 1 credit)
Students learn the impact of world cultures on our society through the study of world affairs, regional studies, and cultural
awareness. Regions of study for this course are Russia, Latin America, and Europe. Students also learn about citizenship,
character, Air Force heritage & traditions, and individual self-control. Students participate in military drill and ceremonies
execution and performance, and learn how drill helps the individual, builds the team, and develops leaders. Students
participate in a physical training program to reach fitness goals and encourage life-long wellness. [Fall 2018]

480029 AFJROTC: Leadership and Exploration of Space (18 Weeks/ 1 credit)
Students learn the basics of space exploration including orbits & trajectories, spacecraft & launch vehicles, and space-
systems operations. Students also learn theories of wellness, health, and fitness and US citizenship and government.
Students participate in military drill and ceremonies execution and performance, and learn how drill helps the individual,
builds the team, and develops leaders. Students participate in a physical training program to reach fitness goals and
encourage life-long wellness. [Spring 2019]

480032 AFJROTC: Leadership and Survival (18 Weeks/ 1 credit)
Students learn skills & knowledge to successfully perform fundamental tasks for survival, using basic Air Force survival
training. Students also learn management basics, theories, and approaches and planning & decision making. Students
participate in military drill and ceremonies execution and performance, and learn how drill helps the individual, builds the
team, and develops leaders. Students participate in a physical training program to reach fitness goals and encourage life-
long wellness. [Fall 2020]

480031 AFJROTC: Leadership and Cultural Studies – Part I (18 Weeks/ 1 credit)
Students learn the impact of world cultures on our society through the study of world affairs, regional studies, and cultural
awareness. Regions of study for this course are the Middle East, Asia, and Africa. Students also learn how to organize to
manage change, stress, and innovation and to lead individuals & groups. Students participate in military drill and ceremonies
execution and performance, and learn how drill helps the individual, builds the team, and develops leaders. Students
participate in a physical training program to reach fitness goals and encourage life-long wellness. [Spring 2021]

                 ARMY JUNIOR ROTC

The Army Junior ROTC teaches citizenship, leadership, and aerospace science. It is NOT a military recruitment program;
students incur NO military service obligation. The objectives of the program are to teach students patriotism, citizenship,
and personal obligation to community/national goals, aerospace basics, leadership, and life skills. Physical fitness is
emphasized in each course. Military drill is used to teach leadership and discipline and to give students opportunities to
practice leadership skills. Students can participate in many outside activities (field trips, leadership schools, drill meets,
parades, military balls, model rocketry, and community service projects.) Courses have no prerequisites, and students may
take courses in any sequence.
For each Army JROTC course:

     1. Students are required to properly wear the ARJROTC uniform one day a week and on special occasions
     2. Students must sign an agreement to adhere to ARJROTC grooming standards for correct uniform wear (including

          proper hair length for males.)
     3. A fee is required.

          ARJROTC fulfills the LIFE physical education state requirement.

ARMY JROTC Leadership Education and Training I (LETI)
18 weeks/1 credit
A course that provides first year cadets with classroom and laboratory instruction in the history, customs, traditions, and
purpose of the Army JROTC. Emphasis is placed on leadership skills, principles, values and attributes, and diversity. **Upon
successful completion of LETI, students may earn credit for the graduation requirements of Career Prep A and B.

ARMY JROTC Leadership Education and Training II (LETII)
18 weeks/1 credit
A course designed to provide intermediate instruction in leadership and citizenry, and the expansion of skills taught in LETI.
Emphasis is placed on communication techniques, cadet challenges, American citizenship, map reading, and the role of the
U.S. Army.

                                                                                27]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[ARMY JROTC Leadership Education and Training III (LETIII)
18 weeks/1 credit
A course designed to provide advanced instruction in leadership and citizenry, communication, history and career
opportunities, and technology awareness. Students will have hands-on experiences as teacher/leaders within the cadet
battalion.
ARMY JROTC Leadership Education and Training IV (LETIV)
18 weeks/1 credit
A course that provides opportunities for students to demonstrate leadership potential in an assigned command or staff
position within the cadet battalion organizational structure. Emphasis is placed on negotiation skills and management
principles.

                                    WORK-BASED LEARNING

Work-Based Learning (formerly Cooperative Learning)

Work-Based Experience-First Credit                   Work-Based Experience-Third Credit

Work-Based Experience-Second Credit                  Work-Based Experience-Fourth Credit

18 weeks/1 credit

Prerequisite: Teacher Approval

Work-based learning is a major component of career and technical education. Improved skills lead to higher efficiency

and the availability of a better-trained labor pool that encourages business growth and productivity. Well-managed work-

based learning experiences build confidence in the school system and have benefits for the student, employer, mentor,

school, and community. Options for WBL include paid employment and unpaid internships. Students may enroll in WBL 1

or 2 consecutive blocks. 140 hours of paid work or internship work must be obtained per block. For example, if a student

is enrolled in 3rd and 4th block they will be required to have 280 hours in paid time or unpaid internship time. WBL is open

to Juniors and Seniors who have completed Career Preparedness A and B. Students must complete a WBL application

and screening process.

                                     THE ARTS

Number                                         THEATRE ARTS                 Credit  Fee  AP Exam

 280071                                     Course                            1.0   $20  Exam Fee
 280072                                                                       1.0   $20  Exam Fee
 280073  Theatre Level I, Beginning Drama                                     1.0   $20
 280074  Theatre Level II, Intermediate Drama                                 1.0   $20
 280079  Theatre Level III, Advanced Drama**                                  1.0   $20
 280079  Theatre Level IV, Advanced Drama**                                   1.0   $20
 280079  Theatre Designing/Technical Theatre                                  1.0   $20
 280076  Intermediate Technical Theatre                                       1.0   $20
         Advanced Technical Theatre
 280093  Advanced Theatre Production **                                       1.0   $25
 280094                                                                       1.0   $25
 280095                                         VISUAL ARTS                   1.0   $25
 280096                                                                       1.0   $25
 280107  Visual Arts Level I Beginning Art                                    1.0   $25
 280101  Visual Arts Level II Intermediate Art                                1.0
         Visual Arts Level III** Studio Seminar                                     $25
 280102  Visual Arts Level IV** Advanced Studio Seminar                       1.0
         Visual Art Elective** Advanced Art (Fall)                                  $30
 280051  AP Art History (does not meet Art Education requirement) (Spring)    1.0   $30
 280053  AP Studio Art Drawing**(does not meet Art Ed. requirement)           1.0
         (Spring)

                                           PERFORMING ARTS
                                          FALL SEMESTER COURSES

         Vocal I (Mixed Chorus)
         Vocal II (Jet Choir or Patriot Singers)

                                     28]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[280055 Vocal III** Patriot Singers (BJHS) (Spring)                     1.0 $30

280057 Vocal IV**Advanced Treble Choir (BJHS) (Spring)                 1.0 $30

280032 Instrumental Level I, Piano I                                   0.5 $20

280034 Instrumental Level II, Piano II                                 0.5 $20

907824 Jazz Band (BJHS)                                                0.5

280031 Instrumental Level I** Marching Band / Competition Band (Fall)  1.0 $50

280037 Instrumental Level IV, Percussion Marching Band (Fall)          1.0 $50

280011 Dance Level I**Color Guard (BJHS) (Fall)                        1.0 $50

280012 Dance Level II**Dance Team (BJHS) (Fall)                        1.0 $50

280011 Dance Level I**Color Guard and Dance Line – Band (JCHS) (Fall)  1.0 $50

280012 Dance Level II**Competition Dance Team (JCHS) (Fall)            1.0 $50

280033 Instrumental Level II**, Concert Band (Spring)                  1.0 $50

280035 Instrumental Level III**, Wind Ensemble (Symphonic Band) (Spring) 1.0 $50

280037 Instrumental Level IV**, Spring Percussion (Indoor Drum Line)   1.0 $50

280039 Instrumental Techniques and Music Theory                        1.0 $12

280039aa Guitar Level I (JCHS)                                         0.5

280024 AP Music Theory (does not meet Art Education requirement)       1.0        Exam Fee

Denotes if Teacher Approval/Audition is required.**Check your schools’ website for audition dates and times.

                                        THE ARTS

THEATRE ARTS

Theatre I (Beginning Drama)
18 weeks/1 credit
Students will learn theatre history, basic acting technique (including stage directions), basic staging concepts, and production
components. Topics such as improvisation, auditioning, pantomime, readers’ theatre, and vocal presentation will be studied.
Students will participate in competition (fall) and perform plays for an audience.

Theatre II (Intermediate Drama)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Theatre I
Focuses on the performance aspects of drama such as improvisation, monologues, duets, and ensemble acting. Topics
such as staging techniques, pantomime, reader’s theatre, and technical theatre will be covered in greater detail with
participation in published plays, as well as student-written monologues, duets, and solos.

Theatre III (Advanced Drama) (Fall)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Intermediate Drama AND Teacher Approval
Advanced acting techniques and includes directing, dramatic literature study, and technical theatre components. Students
will participate in competition and perform a full length play.

Theatre IV (Advanced Drama) (Spring)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Intermediate Drama AND Teacher Approval
Advanced acting techniques and includes directing, dramatic literature study, and technical theatre components. Students
will participate in competition and perform a full length play.

Theatre, Design Tech (Technical Theatre)
18 weeks/1 credit
Design, implement, and execute lighting and sound designs using a variety of lighting and sound systems. Students will
develop costume, scene, and makeup designs for ongoing productions as well as individual portfolios.

                                                    29]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Intermediate Technical Theatre
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Theatre, Design Tech
Design, implement, and execute lighting and sound designs using a variety of lighting and sound systems. Development of
costume, scene, and makeup designs for ongoing productions as well as individual portfolios for secondary and post-
secondary competition.

Theatre, Designing/Technical Theatre (Advanced)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Intermediate Technical Theatre AND Teacher Approval
Advanced light board programming skills, advanced sound system programming and scenic design construction
techniques. Live performance technology, venue management skills and assume leadership roles in technical theatre
positions running school performances for a variety of school groups. Emphasis on theatre management and advanced
theatre technology.

Advanced Theatre Production
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Audition
Students will experience the complete production process as they prepare multiple play. Students will also prepare
monologues and duets for competition and college scholarship auditions. Students will work with guest artists to learn theatre
history, styles, and professional theatre. After school rehearsals, performances, and festival trips are required. Additional
fees are required in order to cover the cost of transportation, festival registration, rights/royalties and production expenses.
Fundraising opportunities will be available to cover the fees. *Students who audition and are accepted to the Advanced
Theatre Production class are required to take both the fall and spring semester courses.

VISUAL ARTS

Visual Arts I (Beginning Art)
18 weeks/1 credit
Provides a foundation for additional art courses that follow. This course is primarily devoted to providing systemic
presentation of various art processes, theories, and historical developments. The approach to art experiences during this
time is experimental in terms of materials but structured in terms of providing students a strong foundation in design, drawing,
and vocabulary.

Visual Arts II (Intermediate Art)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Art I
Continues building on Art 1 skills, providing a stronger, broader, foundation for the more advanced Art courses which follow.
This course is devoted primarily to the conscious and systemic presentation of various art procedures, theories and historical
developments. While the approach to art experiences during this time is experimental in terms of materials, it is still structured
in terms of providing a strong foundation in design, drawing, painting, and vocabulary.

Visual Arts III* (Studio Seminar)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Art II AND Teacher Approval
Focuses on in-depth art experiences. It is flexible in scope, allowing students to make choices from a broad range of art
disciplines. The approach is accelerated as students continue to build on a strong foundation of basics.

                        Visual Arts IV* (Advanced Studio Seminar)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Art III AND Teacher Approval
Students select the area or areas of personal interest in which they desire to work in depth. Students explore increasingly
complicated, challenging processes and media and develop personal style and critical evaluation skills. Course is
accelerated as students begin to prepare portfolio work.

                                                                                30]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Visual Art Elective* (Advanced Art) (Fall)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Art 4 AND Portfolio Review
Accelerated portfolio preparation class for students concentrating on art as a career. Students will produce a body of work
for several portfolios that will compete statewide and nationally for recognition, awards and scholarships. Portfolio review
and teacher approval required.

Advanced Placement Studio Art Drawing (Spring)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Advanced Art and Portfolio review
AP Studio Art is a portfolio-based course. The AP Studio Art Drawing portfolio is designed for students who are seriously
interested in the practical experience of art. AP Studio Art is not based on a written exam; instead, students submit
portfolios for evaluation at the end of the school year. AP Studio Art Drawing sets a national standard for performance in
the visual arts that contributes to the significant role the arts play in academic environments. Participation in national AP
test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course. This course does not meet the Arts Education
requirement.

                        *This course is available as a blended course through Options Open. See your counselor for
                        more information

Advanced Placement Art History (Spring)
18 weeks/1 credit
This Advanced Placement course is accelerated in rigor and pace. Students will study Western and non-western art; cultural
influences in art; prehistoric through contemporary art; discovery and preservation of art, aesthetics; criticism; analysis and
interpretation. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course. This course
does not meet the Arts Education requirement.

                        *This course is available as a blended course through Options Open. See your counselor for
                        more information.

PERFORMING ARTS

Vocal I (Mixed Chorus)
18 weeks/1 credit
Introduces students to performance of a varied repertoire of vocal music. Fundamentals of musical history, theory, sight
singing and proper vocal technique are emphasized. Winter/Spring term is a continuation of Fall term and is taught at a
more advanced level. Students wishing to participate in Winter/Spring term should enroll in this course both terms.
Requirements: purchase of a uniform, rehearsals, and performances outside regular school hours.

Vocal II
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Audition Required
In this class, students experience and participate in the performance of varied repertoire of challenging vocal music. This
course includes musical history, theory, sight singing and proper vocal techniques. Students must enroll for both terms.
Additional requirements: purchase of a uniform, rehearsals and performances outside regular school hours.

            Vocal III (Spring)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Audition Required
In this class, students experience and participate in the performance of varied repertoire of challenging vocal music. This
course includes musical history, theory, sight singing and proper vocal techniques. Students must enroll for both terms.
Additional requirements: purchase of a uniform, rehearsals and performances outside regular school hours.

                                                                                31]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Vocal IV (Advanced Treble Choir)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Audition Required
This advanced chorus class is for students who are in their 4th and subsequent semesters of high school chorus. Students
selected, based on audition during the spring semester for the previous year, experience and participate in the
performance of varied repertoire of challenging vocal music. This course includes more advanced concepts in musical
history, theory, sight singing and proper vocal techniques. Students
must enroll for both terms. Additional requirements: purchase of a uniform, rehearsals and performances and competitions
outside regular school hours.

Instrumental I (Piano I)
9 weeks/0.5 credit
This is an introductory course open to any student who has had no formal piano/keyboard training. Students will perform
alone and in groups, interpret basic musical notation, define and use fundamental musical terms, discuss the various stylistic
periods of musical history, and listen to and evaluate performances by peers as well as recorded performances by
professional musicians.

Instrumental II (Piano II)
9 weeks/0.5 credit
Prerequisite: Piano I AND Teacher Approval
Students will perform alone and in groups, interpret basic musical notation, define and use fundamental musical terms,
discuss the various stylistic periods of musical history, and listen to and evaluate performances by peers as well as recorded
performances by professional musicians.

            Jazz Band
9 weeks/0.5 credit
Prerequisite: music audition
This is an audition-based ensemble in both fall and spring semesters and provides an opportunity for students to participate
in a performing ensemble. Each ensemble will rotate their meeting time each week. One ensemble will meet two days a
week during the zero block, while the other ensemble would meet two days a week during the 5th block. Then the ensembles
would alternate their meeting times the following week.

                        *This course is available at BJHS as a blended course through Options Open. Please see your
                        counselor for details.

Marching Band (Fall)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: summer band camp (BJHS)
This is a performance-based class. Students must audition for placement in this group in the spring of the previous year.
Musical knowledge is required. Summer band camp, other expenses, and after-school activities are required. This course
satisfies the state course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

Competition Band (Fall)
Prerequisite: music audition, summer band camp
This is a performance-based class. Students must audition for placement in this group in the spring of the previous year
and the roster is finalized during summer band camp based on instrumentation needs. Musical knowledge and experience
is required. Summer band camp, other expenses, and after school activities are required. This course satisfies the state
course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

Percussion Marching Band (Fall)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: audition and summer band camp
This is a performance-based class for students who play percussion instruments. Additional fees will be paid to the Band
Boosters in order to cover the cost of transportation, uniforms, and equipment. Fundraising opportunities will be available to
cover the fee paid to the Band Boosters. Requirements: purchase of uniform, rehearsals and performances outside regular
school hours. This course satisfies the state course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

                                                                                32]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Dance I (Color Guard) (Fall)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: audition required
Designed to study all aspects of flag and/or rifle performance including practice on fundamental marching techniques.
Summer band camp, uniform purchase, other expenses, and after-school activities are required. This course satisfies the
state course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

            Dance II (Dance Team) (Fall)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: audition required
Designed to study elements of movement and dance—time, space, and energy—as compositional components; technical
and perception skills; awareness and analysis of movement sequences; spontaneous creation, critical evaluations;
understanding of basic concepts through Dance team performances and competitions. This course satisfies the state
course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

                   Color Guard and Dance Line (Band) (Fall)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: audition required
Designed to study all aspects of flag and/or rifle performance including practice on fundamental marching techniques.
Summer band camp, uniform purchase, other expenses, and after-school activities are required. This course satisfies the
state course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

                   Competition Dance Team (Fall)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: audition required
Designed to study elements of movement and dance—time, space, and energy—as compositional components; technical
and perception skills; awareness and analysis of movement sequences; spontaneous creation, critical evaluations;
understanding of basic concepts through Dance team performances and competitions. This course satisfies the state
course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

Instrumental Techniques & Music Theory
18 weeks/1 credit
Students will learn reading, writing and structure of music. Students will also have individualized practice time on the
instrument of their choice. Since the class is both individualized, and is taught in small groups, there are no prerequisites for
this course. Students must provide their instruments. This course can be repeated as determined by the teacher.

                   Guitar Level 1
9 weeks/0.5 credit
This course provides students with the opportunity to learn the basics of playing guitar and music making. Objectives of
the course include playing chords, scales, and melodies as well as the basics of reading music, lead sheets, and tablature.
This provides students with the skills needed to accompany a singer, participate in a band, and write original music.
Additionally, guitar history, cultural influence, and instrument maintenance will be discussed and analyzed. The curriculum
for the class is designed for a beginner as well as someone who has previously never played guitar. Students will need to
provide their own guitar, however there is no requirement for quality.

                                                                                33]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[Concert Band (Spring)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: audition required
This course offers the basics of instrumental music. Additional fees will be paid to the Band Boosters in order to cover the
cost of transportation, uniforms, and equipment. Fundraising opportunities will be available to cover the fee paid to the Band
Boosters. Requirements: purchase of uniform, rehearsals and performances outside regular school hours.

Wind Ensemble—formerly Symphonic Band (Spring)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: audition and participation in Marching Band—BJHS requirement
This is a performance-based class. Students must audition for placement in this group in the spring of the previous year.
Musical knowledge is required. Additional fees will be paid to the Band Boosters in order to cover the cost of transportation,
uniforms, and equipment. Fundraising opportunities will be available to cover the fee paid to the Band Boosters.
Spring Percussion—formerly Indoor Drum Line
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: audition required
This is a performance-based class for students who play percussion instruments. Additional fees will be paid to the Band
Boosters in order to cover the cost of transportation, uniforms, and equipment. Fundraising opportunities will be available to
cover the fee paid to the Band Boosters. Requirements: purchase of uniform, rehearsals and performances outside regular
school hours. This course satisfies the state course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

AP Music Theory (Spring)
18 weeks/1 credit
This Advanced Placement course is a high level study of music theory, composition, and aural skills. Prior participation in
an instrumental or vocal performing organization, OR prior private music lessons is strongly encouraged. Participation in
the national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course. This course does not meet Art
Education requirement.

         ENGLISH

Number                                  ENGLISH CORE              Credit  Fee AP Exam Fee
                                   Course
 200005                                                              1.0  $20 Exam Fee
 200007  English Grade 9                                             1.0  $20 Exam Fee
 200009  English Grade 9 PreAP, Advanced                             1.0
 200011  English Grade 10                                            1.0  Fee AP Exam Fee
 200013  English Grade 10 PreAP, Advanced                            1.0
 200014  English Grade 11                                            1.0   $5
 200016  English Grade 11 Honors                                     1.0  $20
 200017  AP English Language and Composition                         1.0  $20
 200018  English Grade 12                                            1.0
 200020  English Grade 12 Honors                                     1.0
 300001  AP English Literature & Composition                         1.0
         ELL English
Number                                                            Credit
                                    ENGLISH ELECTIVES
 200032                            Course                            0.5
 200042                                                              0.5
 300001  Composition Expository (Requirement for BJHS)               0.5
 300001  Public Speaking                                             1.0
 200026  ELL Reading for Success                                     0.5
 200033  ELL Newcomer Orientation                                    1.0
 200036  Literature, Mythology and Fable (Myths & Legend)            1.0
         Creative Writing (Writer’s Studio)
 802202  Creative Writing II (JCHS Literary Magazine—BJHS            1.0
         Literary Magazine in Multimedia Publications)
         School Publications (Yearbook Fall)

                                                              34]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[802202   School Publications Spring (Yearbook Spring)  1.0
 802202   School Publications (JCJetStream.com)         1.0 $20
200036aa  Innovations/Inquiry Based Learning            1.0
 802200   Enrichment (Test Prep ACT)                    0.5 $20
 802200   Enrichment (Test Prep ACT Senior Focus)       0.5 $20
 802200   Enrichment (Test Prep PSAT)                   0.5 $20
 200037   Reading Lab                                   1.0

ENGLISH

Graduation requirements: Four credits to include the equivalent of English 9, English 10, English 11, and English 12.

English 9
18 weeks/1 credit
The purpose of this course is to expose students to a variety of fundamental learning opportunities that focus on the
development of literature appreciation through critical thinking strategies, grammar enhancement, communication building,
reading proficiency, writing analysis, and oral presentation skills. This course satisfies the state requirement for one of the
four English credits needed for graduation. Summer reading is required and is provided in the Spring Semester.

English 9 PreAP
18 weeks/1 credit
Honors Credit Awarded
This accelerated paced course will help prepare students for Advanced Placement English Language or Advanced
Placement English Literature. English Honors provides students with experiences to enrich and expand their acquisition of
grammar and communication skills, appreciation of literature and selected classics, organization and presentation of ideas
and concepts, and development of critical thinking skills as demonstrated through analytical writing while cultivating a variety
of individual writing styles. Summer reading is required. The summer reading list is provided in the Spring Semester.

English 10
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: English 9
Course covers Early American Literature (pre-1900) through reading, writing, grammar, and vocabulary activities. In
addition, students will interact with expository texts frequently. This course fulfills the requirements needed for post-
secondary education including college preparation. Summer reading is required. The summer reading list is provided in the
Spring Semester.

English 10 PreAP
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: English 9
Honors Credit Awarded
This accelerated pace course covers Early American Literature (pre-1900) through reading, writing, grammar, and
vocabulary activities. In addition, students will interact with expository texts frequently. This course provides skills for literary
analysis of readings, as well as advanced composition that will prepare students for Advanced Placement English Language
or Advanced Placement English Literature. The summer reading list is provided in the Spring Semester.

English 11
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: English 10
Contemporary American Literature (1900-present) will be analyzed with strong emphasis on writing styles. Vocabulary
expansion, comprehension, and word recognition are emphasized in reading activities. This course coordinates literature,
composition, grammar, and vocabulary through representative readings from historical documents, essays, dramas, short
stories, and novels of significant American writers. This course fulfills the requirements needed for post-secondary education
including college preparation. Summer reading is required. The summer reading list is provided in the Spring Semester.

          35]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[English 11 Honors
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisites: English 10
Honors Credit Awarded
This accelerated pace course covers Contemporary/American Literature (1900-present) with strong emphasis on vocabulary
and composition integration. Vocabulary expansion, comprehension, and word recognition are emphasized in reading
activities. This course provides skills for rhetorical analysis of readings, as well as advanced composition that will prepare
students for Advanced Placement English Literature. Summer reading is required. The summer reading list is provided in
the Spring Semester.

Advanced Placement English Language and Composition
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: English 10
This course is accelerated in rigor and pace of a college level course. It provides skills for rhetorical analysis of writings, as
well as advanced composition (portfolio, essays and on-demand assignments). It is designed for advanced readers and
writers who are eager to examine the use of language in depth. Summer reading is required. The summer reading list is
provided in the Spring Semester. This course fulfills the English 11 core requirement. Participation in the national AP test
is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

English 12
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: English 11
This course is a survey of classical British Literature from the Anglo-Saxon period to the Modern Age. In addition, students
will explore and analyze expository text and engage in critical listening, speaking, reading, and writing activities designed to
integrate the strands of the language arts and further develop thinking and problem-solving abilities. This course fulfills the
requirements needed for post-secondary education including college preparation. Summer reading is required. The summer
reading list is provided in the Spring Semester.

English 12 Honors
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: English 11
Honors Credit Awarded
This accelerated pace course covers a survey of British Literature from the Anglo-Saxon period to the Modern Age. Students
will engage in critical listening, speaking, reading, and writing activities with a strong emphasis on vocabulary. This course
fulfills the requirements needed for post-secondary education including college preparation. Summer reading is required.
The summer reading list is provided in the Spring Semester.

Advanced Placement English Literature and Composition
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: English 11 or AP Language and Composition
This course is accelerated in rigor and pace of a college level elective course. It provides skills for literary analysis of
literature, as well as advanced composition. This course fulfills the requirements needed for post-secondary education
including college preparation. Summer reading is required. The summer reading list is provided in the Spring Semester. This
course fulfills the English 12 core requirement. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor
of this course.

ELL English
18 weeks/1 credit
Content-based ELL Instruction
This course will count as an English credit for students enrolled in our English Language Learners Program. It is designed
for students who need an individualized, structured English course to study grammar and reading skills.

                                                                                36]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[English Electives

            Composition Expository (Freshman Comp)
9 weeks/0.5 credit
The purpose of this class is to help students improve their writing skills using narrative, persuasive and expository modes
of writing and other forms of communication, including speaking and listening skills. Students will present their end
products using a variety of methods, including print and technology. The primary writing focus is on persuasive and
expository writing. This class does not fulfill the English 9 requirement for graduation.

                        *This course is available online, through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for
                        more information.

Public Speaking
9 weeks/ 0.5 credit
This course will provide a basic overview of the communications process and provide students with an opportunity to begin
developing public speaking skills. Persuasive, informative and expository speeches will be delivered. Short units on
interview techniques, debate procedures and stage guidelines will be included.

Literature, Mythology and Fable (Myth and Legend)
9 weeks/0.5 credit
This class will offer students an opportunity to study world cultures through mythology, folklore, and legends. This class will
not only include classical mythology but also multicultural folk literature from such areas as African American, Native
American, the Orient, and others. Local legend and folklore will be highlighted through story telling from the community

Creative Writing (Writers’ Studio)
18 weeks/1 credit
Students will study and write in the following genres: poetry, prose, creative nonfiction, theatre, journalism, comics,
television, and film. They will also employ graphic design principles in the creation of multimedia and web design projects.
They will submit their final portfolios for literary magazine consideration and participate in a variety of writing contests.

Creative Writing II (Literary Magazine)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Creative Writing
This course engages students in becoming skilled writers of fiction, poetry, creative non-fiction, and screenplay. Students
will develop writing techniques which will enhance structure, syntax, diction, characters, setting, and basic plot. Students will
investigate publication opportunities as well as possible career avenues in fields of writing. Students will further their writing
through self-reflection and workshops with published authors. Students will create, contribute, and publish the James
Clemens Literary Magazine. Bob Jones Literary Magazine is created and published through the Multimedia
Publications course: number 410017.

                   School Publications (JCJetStream.com)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: teacher approval
Students create, design, and publish the school's online student "newspaper," entitled Jet Stream (jcjetstream.com).
Students will use industry-standard web-based tools to create and publish custom content including opinion articles, school
culture pieces, global news stories, student spotlights, and many other types of content geared toward student expression
and life. Requirements for becoming a staff member are as follows: fill out an application, obtain two recommendations (one
of which must be a recent English teacher).

School Publications (Yearbook Fall)
School Publications (Yearbook Spring)
Each 18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Teacher Approval
In this course, students create, publish, and market the school’s yearbook. Yearbook staff members learn and use various
publishing tools such as Adobe InDesign and PhotoShop; conduct interviews of students and faculty; take pictures at
school events; write journalistic style articles; work under established deadlines; sell ads to local businesses; and create

                                                                                37]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[promotional campaigns. Because the school yearbook is a costly undertaking affecting the entire student body, staff
members may be required to stay after school on occasion in order to complete deadlines. Requirements for becoming a
staff member are as follows: fill out an application, be interviewed by the advisor and present staff, and obtain two
recommendations (one of which should be the present English teacher), and possess a B or better in English. Students
are highly encouraged to take both fall and spring courses. This course is required for BJHS students.

Innovations/Inquiry-Based Learning Class
18 weeks/1 credit
Innovations is a project-based learning environment where students explore, create, partner, and produce both individually
and in groups. Collaboration with business and industry partners will be at the heart of this class as students identify and
pursue projects that are relevant to the community and will make an impact on society. Innovations allows students to
pursue their own academic and research interests, enabling students to play a significant role in identifying innovative
opportunities. Projects that students pursue in this class must contain evidence from the Alabama Courses of Study;
exploration into content areas may be different for each student.

Enrichment (Test Prep: ACT)
9 weeks/0.5 credit
Prerequisite: Geometry
This open enrollment course provides all students necessary taking skills and content knowledge to improve their ACT
scores and will include diagnostic testing, direct instruction, and practice tests of ACT. Recommend course pairing with
Career Preparedness B (Grade 10).

                        *This course is available online through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for more
                        information.

Enrichment (Test Prep ACT Senior Focus)
Fall semester 1st 9 weeks/0.5 credit
This course is designated for seniors who need to build test taking skills prior to the senior October administration of the
ACT.

Enrichment (Test Prep PSAT)
Fall semester/1st 9 weeks/0.5 credit
By invitation only
This course is designated for incoming 10th graders and other 11th graders who have shown National Merit potential by
scoring in the 85th or above percentile on their last PSAT. It will be targeted to assisting these students in pursuing National
Merit distinction.

Reading Lab
18 weeks/01.0 credit
Reading lab delivers highly concentrated core curriculum to strengthen skills such as reading literature, reading
informational text, writing, speaking and listening, and language. This course does not fulfill any of the four English credits
required for graduation.

ELL Reading for Success
9 weeks/0.5 credit
ELL elective skills building course
Builds reading skills through the utilization of high interest reading materials and will address the specific needs of ELL
students in the area of reading and reading comprehension.

ELL Newcomer Orientation
18 weeks/1 credit
ELL elective orientation course
Addresses the specific needs of recent immigrant students, especially those with limited or interrupted schooling in their
home countries. Major goals of this orientation are to acculturate the student to the United States culture, school system,
and orient the student to his/her new community.

                                                                                38]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[HEALTH, PHYSICAL EDUCATION, DRIVER’S ED

Number                                 Course           Credit          Fee

 250002   Health                                          0.5            $30
290001aa  Driver and Traffic Safety Education (Fall)      0.5            $30
290001ab  Driver and Traffic Safety Education (Spring)    0.5   uniform/locker fee
          Lifelong Individual Fitness, LIFE               1.0            TBD
 240002   Sports Officiating Certification                1.0
 240004

HEALTH, PHYSICAL EDUCATION & DRIVER’S ED

Graduation requirements: One and ½ credits to include the equivalent of one credit Life PE (or an equivalent) and ½
credit of Health (or an equivalent). Check with your school for athletic PE specific course numbers.

Health
9 weeks/0.5 credit
The course will consider the relationship between lifestyle health-related issues, including sexual responsibility, family
issues, mental health, and personal safety. In addition, an application of proper nutrition, weight control, fitness, stress
management, tobacco, drug and alcohol abuse, and emergency care (CPR) will be presented. This required course is
primarily for tenth graders. It should be paired with another 0.5 credit course. Note: Foundations of Health Science is a
substitute for this course.

                        *This course is available online through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for more
                        information.

Driver and Traffic Safety Education
9 weeks/0.5 credit
Driver's Ed is a 0.5 credit elective for students who will be 15 years of age before taking the course. Students must have
their learner’s permit prior to the first day of class or will be rescheduled and assessed a $20 scheduling change fee. The
learner’s permit is required the first day of class.

Lifelong Individualized Fitness Education P.E., LIFE
18 weeks/1 credit
The focus of this state required course is health enhancing physical activity. LIFE provides the knowledge for a lifetime of
healthy living. Through the LIFE course students learn to apply the various aspects of fitness and to assess their own fitness
levels. Students are required to develop and maintain an individual level of fitness that forms the foundation for a healthy
future. LIFE provides students with the knowledge and ability to construct and implement a lifelong plan for physical activity.
LIFE uses a variety of health enhancing physical activities as the vehicle for reinforcing and applying fitness components
and principles. This course satisfies the state course of study for the LIFE PE requirement.

Sports Officiating Certification
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: LIFE PE: Students must be age 16 or older, or turn age 16 during the school year.
This course is an elective that focuses on the professional philosophy and requirements for officiating sports for athletic
contests. This course will cover officiating football, basketball, wrestling, volleyball, soccer, baseball, track and field, and
softball. Upon completion of the course students will be afforded the option to take certification exams for any of the sport
components and become a restricted certified official with the Alabama High School Athletic Association at the middle/junior
high school level.

          39]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[MATH

                                                   MATH CORE

           Number                     Course                   Credit  Fee AP Exam Fee

             210032  Pre-Algebra                               1.0     $20 Exam Fee
             210008                                                    $20 Exam Fee
             210009  Algebra 1A                                1.0     $10 Exam Fee
             210013
             210014  Algebra 1B                                1.0
             210010
             210012  Geometry A                                1.0
             210015
             210036  Geometry B                                1.0
             210016
             210017  Geometry                                  1.0
             210017
             210018  Geometry PreAP                            1.0
             210034
             210020  Algebraic Connections                     1.0
             210023
             210025  Algebra with Finance                      1.0
             210026
             210027  Algebra II                                1.0
             210033
                     Algebra II with Trigonometry              1.0
MATH
                     Algebra II with Trigonometry PreAP        1.0

                     Discrete Mathematics                      1.0

                     Analytical Mathematics                    1.0

                     Precalculus PreAP                         1.0

                     Calculus A (PreAP)                        1.0

                     Calculus AB, AP                           1.0

                     Calculus BC, AP                           1.0

                     Statistics, AP                            1.0

                     Math Lab                                  1.0

Graduation requirements: Four credits to include Algebra 1, Geometry, and Algebra II with Trigonometry or its equivalent.

Pre-Algebra
18 weeks/1 elective credit
The Pre-Algebra course is designed to reinforce mathematical concepts necessary to be successful in Algebra I, Geometry,
and Algebra II. An integral part of the course will be developing mathematical study skills and learning strategies. The
course starts with an in depth discussion of the real number system to include fractions, decimals, integers, radicals,
exponents, and order of operations. The course also includes units that reinforce expressions and equations, functions,
geometry, and statistics. Pre-Algebra counts as elective credit only; it does not count as a core math credit.

Math Lab
18 weeks/1.0 credit
This course is designed for students who need support with math-related topics such as properties of number systems,
algebraic thinking, and geometry. Students will receive individualized help on the concepts and skills that they need to
successfully complete their math course. It is recommended that this course be taken in conjunction with a required math
course. This course does not fulfill any of the four math credits required for graduation.

Algebra 1A and Algebra 1B
Each course is 18 weeks/1 credit
This two-part course sequence satisfies the Algebra 1 requirement for graduation. Content in this course, along with Algebra
1B, will be assessed as part of graduation requirements. Calculator use is encouraged. Algebra 1A and Algebra 1B counts
as one full credit each.

                                                         40]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Geometry A and Geometry B
Each course is 18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra 1 or Algebra A/B
This two-part course sequence is designed for a student who may prefer a slower instructional pace and would benefit from
more practice and hands-on experiences. Geometry A and Geometry B count as one full credit each.

Geometry
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra 1 or Algebra1A/B
Provides increased student understanding of shapes and properties with emphasis on practical tasks, recreations, sciences,
and the arts and the development of concepts related to 2 and 3 dimensional figures. Constructing, drawing, measuring,
and modeling are used to further the understanding of properties of geometric figures and to represent problem situations.
Concepts, such as parallelism, perpendicularity, congruency, similarity, and symmetry are studied in many contexts.
Translations, reflections, and rotations are used to describe how objects move. Classifying figures in terms of congruency
and similarity and applying these relationships are treated fully in this course. Calculator use is encouraged.

Geometry PreAP
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra 1 or Algebra1 A/B
Honors Credit Awarded
This course covers the same topics as Geometry but places a higher emphasis on advanced Algebra 1 concepts and solving
real world problems by applying geometric concepts in modeling situations. Additional material is also covered such as the
unit circle. Because of the additional material and increased rigor, this course will have a faster pace than Geometry. A
calculator with trigonometric functionality is encouraged.

Algebraic Connections
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra 1 and Geometry
Algebraic Connections is a course designed for students who wish to increase their mathematical knowledge and skills prior
to enrollment in the Algebra II course or the Algebra II with Trigonometry course. Algebraic Connections expands upon the
concepts of Algebra 1 and Geometry, with an emphasis on application-based problems. This course provides opportunities
to incorporate the use of technology through its emphasis on applying functions to make predictions and to calculate
outcomes.

Algebra with Finance
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra 1 and Geometry
Algebra with Finance is a college and career preparatory course that integrates algebra, precalculus, probability and
statistics, calculus and geometry to solve financial problems that occur in everyday life. Real-world problems in investing,
credit, banking, auto insurance, mortgages, employment, income taxes, budgeting and planning for retirement are solved
by applying the relevant mathematics that are taught at a higher level. This course may be used as the fourth math
credit required for graduation, replacing Algebra II or Algebra II with Trigonometry credit requirement for Cohort
2017 and beyond.

Algebra II
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra 1 and Geometry
Algebra II is a course designed to extend students’ algebraic knowledge and skills. Students are encouraged to solve
problems using a variety of methods that promote the development of improved communication skills and foster a deeper
understanding of the subject matter. To help students appreciate the power of algebra, applications involving real-life
situations are incorporated throughout the course. Algebra II does not provide sufficient background to prepare students to
pursue higher-level mathematics courses such as Pre-calculus. It is considered a terminal high school mathematics course.
It does, however, meet the NCAA Clearinghouse requirement for Algebra II credit.

                                                                                41]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Algebra II with Trigonometry
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra 1 and Geometry
Provides a more in-depth treatment of algebraic concepts presented in Algebra 1 while introducing several higher-level
topics. Quadratic equations function graphing, systems of equations and inequalities, and trigonometry are topics expanded
in this course. Complex numbers, exponential and logarithmic functions, and matrices are introduced. Statistics and
probability topics include determination of regression line and application of counting principles.

Algebra II with Trigonometry PreAP
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra 1, Geometry
Honors Credit Awarded
Covers quadratic equations, function graphing, systems of equations and inequalities, and trigonometry. Sequences and
series, complex numbers, exponential and logarithmic functions, and matrices are introduced. Statistics and probability
topics include determination of regression line and application of the counting principle. Graphing calculator use is
recommended. Projects and presentations may be included in this course.

Discrete Mathematics
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra II with Trigonometry
Discrete Mathematics expands upon the topics of matrices, combinational reasoning, counting techniques, algorithms,
sequences, series, and their applications. Students are expected to work in both individual and group settings to apply
problem-solving strategies and to incorporate technological tools that extend beyond traditional instructional practices.

                        *This course is offered at JCHS as a blended course through Options Open. See your counselor
                        for more information.

Analytical Math
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra II with Trigonometry
Note: Fulfills one of the four mathematics credits required for graduation. Analytical Mathematics is a course designed for
students who have successfully completed the Algebra II with Trigonometry course. It is considered to be parallel in rigor to
Precalculus. While this course may be taken either prior to or after Precalculus, it is recommended that students who are
interested in postsecondary studies in engineering successfully complete the Precalculus course as well as, where available,
an Advanced Placement or International Baccalaureate calculus course. This course provides a structured introduction to
important areas of emphasis in most postsecondary studies that pursue a concentration in mathematics. Linear algebra,
logic, vectors, and matrices are topics that are given more in-depth coverage than in previous courses. Application-based
problem solving is an integral part of this course. To assist students with numerical and graphical analysis, the use of
advanced technological tools is highly recommended.

Precalculus PreAP
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra II with Trigonometry or Discrete Math
Honors Credit Awarded
This is a college-preparatory course with a rigorous intensity and pace intended for highly motivated students who have
successfully completed Algebra II with Trigonometry. A variety of topics are reviewed and expanded upon, including
trigonometry, complex numbers, functions, graphing and logarithms. Many topics are combined to explore new areas such
as polar coordinates, polar graphing, conic sections, vectors, matrices, polynomial theory and induction proofs. Graphing is
studied in-depth to determine properties of functions. Limits and derivatives are introduced. Many other areas are covered
to give the college-bound student a basis for calculus. Graphing calculator use is encouraged.

Calculus A (PreAP)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Precalculus
Honors Credit Awarded
Calculus A (PreAP) is the beginning calculus for students who have completed Precalculus. This course is an in-depth study
of elementary functions, limits, and differential calculus. Some topics of integration are also introduced. A graphing calculator
is encouraged.

                                                                                42]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Advanced Placement Calculus AB–Spring
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Calculus A
This Advanced Placement course is accelerated in rigor and pace. Advanced Placement (AP) Calculus AB is a continuation
of Calculus A. The primary focus of the course is preparing students for the AP Calculus AB exam. Topics covered include
transcendental functions, techniques of integration, and applications of integration. Also, the material from Calculus A will
be reviewed extensively in preparation for the AB exam. Students are encouraged to provide graphing calculators for use in
this course. Calculus A should be taken in the fall of the school year that a student is taking AP Calculus AB. College
credit at most universities may be earned for Calculus I by scoring a 3, 4, or 5 on the AP Calculus AB Exam. Participation
in the national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.
Advanced Placement Calculus BC–Spring
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Calculus
This Advanced Placement course is accelerated in rigor and pace. Advanced Placement (AP) Calculus BC is a
continuation of Calculus A. The primary focus of the course is preparing students for the AP Calculus BC exam. Topics
covered include transcendental functions, techniques of integration, applications of integration, and infinite series. Also,
the material from Calculus A will be reviewed extensively in preparation for the BC exam. Students are encouraged to
provide graphing calculators for use in this course. Calculus P should be taken in the fall of the school year that a student
is taking AP Calculus BC. College credit at most universities may be earned for Calculus I and II by scoring a 3, 4, or 5 on
the AP Calculus BC Exam. Participation in the national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this
course.
Advanced Placement Statistics
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Precalculus
This Advanced Placement course is accelerated in rigor and pace. This course introduces students to the major concepts
and tools for collecting, analyzing, and drawing conclusions from data. Students are exposed to four conceptual themes:
observing patterns by exploring data, deciding what and how to measure in planning study, producing models using
probability theory and simulation, and making statistical inferences from models. Students should expect an intensive
course requiring the use of a graphing calculator. There will be applications of concepts through written work. A TI-83, TI-
84 or NSPIRE will be utilized in this course. Participation in the national AP test is a mandatory component in the
rigor of this course.

                                                                                43]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[High School Math Courses

(The number in the black oval is the recommended minimum grade for progressing from one course to
the next. Honors level courses have thick borders around the course title, and AP courses have double

                                                                   borders.)

                            Algebra IA                                          Algebra I
                            Algebra IB                                         (8th grade)

               Geometry A                  80                                              85
               Geometry B
                                             Geometry                        Geometry PreAP

Algebra                                                     90                               85
    II
   OR                   80  80                                           Algebra II w/ Trig PreAP

Algebra      Algebraic                                                                   80
  with     Connections
                                                                            Precalculus
Finance
(terminal                                                                       80
courses)

                            Algebra II w/ Trig

                                                    85

Discrete Math

                              Analytical
                            Mathematics

                                                        80

                            AP Statistics                              Calculus A

                                                                80 90

                                                         AP Calculus AB  AP Calculus BC
                                                        44]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[SCIENCE

Number                                     SCIENCE CORE  Credit  Fee AP Exam Fee

 220051                             Course                 1.0    $5
 220011                                                    1.0   $10
 220013  Physical Science                                  1.0   $10
 220044  Biology                                           1.0   $20
 220014  Biology PreAP                                     1.0   $20 Exam Fee
 220017  Molecular Biology                                 1.0   $20
 220029  AP Biology                                        1.0   $10
 220032  Genetics                                          1.0   $20 Exam Fee
 220040  Environmental Science                             1.0   $10
 220063  AP Environmental Science                          1.0   $20
 220061  Marine Science                                    1.0   $20
 220068  Chemistry PreAP                                   1.0   $20
 220064  Chemistry I                                       1.0   $20 Exam Fee
 220034  Chemistry II                                      1.0   $15
 220087  AP Chemistry                                      1.0    $5
 220071  Forensics                                         1.0   $10
 220073  Astronomy                                         1.0   $20 Exam Fee
 220069  Physics                                           1.0   $20 Exam Fee
 220075  AP Physics I                                      1.0   $20 Exam Fee
         AP Physics C: Mechanics
 490015  AP Physics C: Electric/Magnet                     1.0   $20
         Human Body Structures and Functions (Human
         Anatomy & Physiology) Honors

SCIENCE

Graduation Requirements: Four credits to include Biology and a Physical Science (i.e. Physical Science, Chemistry,
Physics). The third and fourth science credits may be used to meet both the science and the CTE course requirement and
must be chosen from the Alabama Course of Study: Science or CTE/AP/IB equivalent courses.

Physical Science
18 weeks/1 credit
Surveys concepts taught in chemistry and physics requires basic math skills, prepares the student for continued study in
science and meets the physical science graduation requirement and is recommended for students going through Algebra
1A and 1B to help better prepare them for Chemistry.

Biology
18 weeks/1 credit
Required for graduation
Biology introduces students to the vast diversity of organisms and the characteristics that define life. Units include
biodiversity, cells, interdependence, genetics, and evolution. Inquiry based laboratory work is required.

Biology PreAP
18 weeks/1 credit
Honors Credit Awarded
This is an accelerated course designed to prepare students for Advanced Placement Biology. The curriculum is compacted
to provide more time for the in-depth study of current topics and presentation of additional topics not usually found in the
regular classroom. Students taking Biology Honors should realize that there is an obligation to do enrichment work outside
the classroom, both in individual studies and in group work. Students should be self-motivated and self-starters. This course
meets the biology graduation requirement.

         45]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Molecular Biology
18 weeks/1 credit
Honors Credit Awarded
Prerequisite: Biology
Corequisite: Chemistry I PreAP or Chemistry I
This course covers basic cell biology, which primarily includes basic chemistry, macromolecules, cell organelles, plasma
membrane, cellular respiration and photosynthesis. This course also includes Mendelian and molecular genetics,
evolutionary theory and processes.

Advanced Placement Biology
18 weeks/1 credit/
Prerequisite: Molecular Biology
This course focuses on organisms, populations, structure and function of plants and animals, including human systems, and
ecology. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

Genetics
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Biology and Chemistry
This course focuses on Mendelian genetics, gene structure and function, inheritance patterns, genetic abnormalities,
biotechnology, and the Human Genome Project. Case studies in biotechnology and scenarios in bioethics help students
understand the implications and complicated issues that are emerging as the science of genetics continues to develop.

Environmental Science
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Chemistry or Physical Science
Focuses on the study of ecological principles and their application to field studies and human interaction. Students will learn
how certain current trends, such as population growth, water pollution, and depletion of natural resources affect the ability
of the human population to sustain itself. Ways to modify these trends to benefit civilization is also strongly emphasized.

Advanced Placement Environmental Science
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Biology and Chemistry
This is a course that provides students with the scientific principles, concepts, and methodologies required to understand
the interrelationships of the natural world, to identify and analyze environmental problems both natural and human-made, to
evaluate the relative risks associated with these problems, and to examine alternative solutions for resolving and/or
preventing them. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

Marine Science
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Biology and a physical science to include Physical Science, Chemistry, or Physics.
This course is a study of the marine environment (oceanography), marine diversity (survey of plants and animals), and
marine ecology. Students will apply concepts and applications from biological and physical sciences to analyze and evaluate
the impacts made on and by the ocean and all that it encompasses.

Chemistry I
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Algebra I
This course focuses on the composition, structure, and behavior of matter. Due to the emphasis on advanced problem-
solving, incorporating algebraic skills, and a variety of laboratory activities, it is highly recommended that students have
earned a “B” or higher average in Algebra I. If a student has taken Algebra IA and IB it is recommended they take Physical
Science before taking Chemistry I to ensure success in Chemistry. It has been generally noted that students in Algebra IA
and IB struggle more with the math in Chemistry I and Physical Science gives more foundation in science computation. This
course meets the physical science graduation requirement.

                                                                                46]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Chemistry I PreAP
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Biology
Corequisite: Algebra II with Trigonometry
Honors Credit Awarded
This is an accelerated course designed to prepare students for success in Advanced Placement Chemistry. This class is
designed to foster independent learning, good study habits, and critical thinking. The course covers the content described
in the Alabama Course of Study and also includes organic chemistry, analytical chemistry techniques, and colligative
properties. This course involves a great deal of mathematical thinking and problem solving. Students are expected to do a
great deal of independent study and come to class prepared to discuss, practice and ask questions.

Chemistry II
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Biology and Chemistry I
Focuses on organic chemistry, biochemistry, and the relevance of these subjects to everyday life. Emphasis is placed on
laboratory investigations and scientific inquiry activities. Math skills required prior to this course include dimensional analysis,
significant figures, calculations with scientific notation, reaction and solution stoichiometry, percentage error, percentage
yield, and logarithms.

Advanced Placement Chemistry
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Chemistry PreAP or Chemistry I
Corequisite: Algebra II with Trigonometry
This course is the equivalent of the first two inorganic college chemistry classes. Topics such as the structure of matter,
kinetic theory of gases, chemical equilibria, chemical kinetics, and the basic concepts of thermodynamics are presented in
considerable depth. Students are expected to do a great deal of independent study and come to class prepared to discuss,
practice and ask questions. Optional practice and resources are provided to all students to encourage students to do the
work necessary to be successful in the class. Lab work is an integral part of the course. Chemistry topics stipulated by the
College Board will be covered in depth and detail. For additional information, visit College Board’s class description.
Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

Forensics
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Chemistry I
Explores the science of crime scene analysis with real life application of Chemistry and Physics and focuses on solving high
level problems, crime scene management, fingerprint collection and analysis, forensic anthropology, forensic odontology,
some forensic pathology, and blood spatter analysis.

Astronomy
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Biology or a physical science to include Physical Science, Chemistry, or Physics.
This course will focus on characteristics and life cycles of stars, formation of the solar system, comparison of planets,
orientation and placement of the Earth in the Milky Way galaxy, formation of galaxies, and theories about the formation of
the universe.

Physics
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Chemistry I and Algebra II with Trigonometry
This science explores the relationship between matter and energy. A strong background in math is recommended.

                                                                                47]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[Advanced Placement Physics I
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisites: Chemistry I, and Algebra II with Trigonometry
Co-requisite: Precalculus
This course is designed to teach the concepts from the Algebra-Based Advanced Placement Physics 1Physics is the science
that deals with the relationship between matter and energy. This course focuses on the big ideas of physics, which
encompass core scientific principles, theories, and processes of the discipline. The framework encourages instruction that
allows students to make connections across domains through a broader way of thinking about the physical world. This is
an accelerated paced course taught on a high math level designed to prepare students to move onto AP Physics C
Mechanical. A strong background in math is recommended. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component
in the rigor of this course. This course will prepare students to take the AP Physics 1 course; although the complete
AP Physics 2 curriculum is not taught in this course, some students may feel prepared to take both the AP Physics
1 and AP Physics 2 exams.

Advanced Placement Physics C Mechanical
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Physics or AP Physics 1
This is a calculus-based physics course equivalent to engineering college physics. Subjects include: motion, forces, energy,
rotation, gravitation, and oscillations. Calculus will be used freely in formulating principles and in solving problems. It is
recommended that Calculus PreAP be taken before this course or simultaneously. Participation in national AP test is a
mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

Advanced Placement Physics C Electricity and Magnetism
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Precalculus and either Physics or AP Physics 1
This is a calculus-based physics course equivalent to engineering college physics. Subjects include: electric fields, Gauss’s
Law, electrical potential, capacitance, DC and AC circuits, magnetic fields, Faraday’s Law, and inductance. Calculus will be
used freely in formulating principles and in solving problems. It is recommended that Calculus PreAP be taken before this
course or simultaneously. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

Human Body Structures and Functions (Human Anatomy & Physiology)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Biology or Biology PreAP
Corequisite: Chemistry
Honors Credit Awarded
Prepares students for biomedical, nursing, and other health-related careers, and is a prerequisite for Health Science
Internship: organized to follow a logical sequence of the ten systems of the human body with emphasis on diseases and
disorders. Laboratory dissection includes anatomical study of a mammal.

                                                                                48]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[SOCIAL SCIENCE

                                SOCIAL SCIENCE CORE

Number                          Course                              Credit Fee AP Exam Fee

230013 World History: 1500 to Present Grade 9                       1.0

230027 AP World History                                             1.0 $30  Exam Fee

230016 United States History I: Beginnings to the Industrial        1.0

        Revolution (Grade 10 Course)

230019  United States History II: the Industrial Revolution to the  1.0
        Present (Grade 11 Course)

230022  AP US History (fall)                                        2.0 $30  Exam Fee
230022  AP US History (spring)

230041 US Government                                                0.5

230051 Economics                                                    0.5

230047 AP US Government and Politics                                1.0 $20  Exam Fee

230054 AP Macroeconomics                                            1.0 $10  Exam Fee

                             SOCIAL SCIENCE ELECTIVES

Number                          Course                              Credit Fee AP Exam Fee

230081 Sociology                                                    1.0

230071 Psychology                                                   1.0

230201 Contemporary World Issues & Civic Engagement                 1.0

230072 AP Psychology                                                1.0 $20  Exam Fee

230062 AP Human Geography                                           1.0 $20  Exam Fee

230029 AP European History                                          1.0 $20  Exam Fee

230089 AP Seminar                                                   1.0 Exam Fee

230084 AP Research                                                  1.0 Exam Fee

802207 Peer Helpers (Student 2 Student)                             1.0 $20

802206 Student Aide**                                               1.0

802209 Student Leadership**                                         1.0

                                **Teacher Approval required

SOCIAL SCIENCES

Graduation requirements: Four credits to include the equivalents of World History and Geography, US History I:
Beginnings to the Industrial Revolution, US History II: the Industrial Revolution to the Present, Government and
Economics.

World History: 1500 to Present (Grade 9 Course)
18 weeks/1 credit
Emphasis is placed on geographic impact, development of civic knowledge/responsibilities, and emerging economic
systems 1500 to present.

Advanced Placement World History

18 weeks/1 credit
Recommended B or above in prior Social Sciences/summer work required
Accelerated in rigor and pace, this course develops a greater understanding of the evolution of global processes and
contacts, in interaction with different types of human societies. This understanding is advanced through a combination of
selective factual knowledge and appropriate analytical skills. The course highlights the nature of changes in international
frameworks and their causes and consequences, as well as comparisons among major societies. Strong reading
comprehension and critical thinking skills will be tested by essay writing, document analysis and outside reading
assignments. Summer assignment is required. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor

of this course.

                                               49]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[United States History I: Beginnings to the Industrial Revolution (Grade 10 Course)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: World History: 1500 to Present
Studies critical issues and events in United States history from Colonial America through 1900. Studies will include the
changing social, political, economic, and cultural forces at work within the nation.

                        *This course is available online at JCHS through the Options Open courses. See your counselor
                        for more information.

United States History II: the Industrial Revolution to the Present (Grade 11 Course)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: United States History I
Studies critical issues and events in United States history from the 1900’s to present day America. Studies will include the
changing social, political, economic, and cultural forces at work within the nation.

                        *This course is available online at JCHS through the Options Open courses. See your counselor
                        for more information.

Advanced Placement US History– Fall/Spring
36 weeks/2 credits
Prerequisite: World History; recommended B or above in prior Social Sciences
Accelerated in rigor and pace, emphasis will be placed on learning to deal analytically with the social, economic and political
issues of American’s past. This course meets the graduation requirement for both Early and Modern U.S. History.
Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

US Government
9 weeks/0.5 credit
Prerequisite: US History I and US History II
This 0.5 credit course is normally paired with Economics and focuses on the nature and theory of civic responsibility,
virtue, and participation. This course is an in-depth study of all three governmental branches.

                        *This course is available online through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for more
                        information.

Economics
9 weeks/0.5 credit
Prerequisite: World History, US History I, and US History II
This 0.5 credit course is normally paired with U.S. Government and focuses mainly on the American economic system’s
concepts and theories; however, other economic systems will be incorporated into the study.

                        *This course is available online through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for more
                        information.

Advanced Placement Government
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: World History, US History I, and US History II
Accelerated in rigor and pace, this course is designed to give students critical perspective on government and politics
within the United States. The course involves generalized political science concepts and political theories. Critical thinking
and analysis skills are used to interpret the American political system. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory
component in the rigor of this course.

Advanced Placement Macroeconomics
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: World History, US History to 1877 Grade 10(Early) & US History from 1877 – Present Grade 11(Modern)
Accelerated in rigor and pace, this course is designed to give the student a thorough understanding of the principles of
economics that apply to an economic system as a whole. The curriculum places particular emphasis on the study of national
income and price determination and develops student familiarity with economic performance measures, economic growth,
and international economics. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

                                                                                50]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[SOCIAL SCIENCE ELECTIVES

(These courses do not satisfy required Social Science credits for graduation.)

Sociology
18 weeks/1 credit
This course focuses on culture and society; social inequalities; social institutions; and social change. Topics included will
broaden students understanding of the influences of genetics, demographics, religion, and personal behaviors upon
society.

Psychology
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is designed to introduce students to the vast and diverse field of psychology. The program teaches students
the principles, concepts, and theories of psychology. Students will gain insight to better understand themselves, their lives,
and their communities.

Contemporary World Issues & Civic Engagement
18 weeks/1 credit
Current events of local, state, national, and international interest; media information analysis, political coverage, and
techniques; analysis of current events from geographical, historical, political, social, and cultural perspectives

Advanced Placement Psychology
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: World History
Accelerated in rigor and pace, this course will introduce students to the systematic and scientific study of behavior and
mental processes of human beings and other animals. Students are exposed to the psychological facts, principles, and
phenomena associated with each of the job for subfields within psychology. They also learn about the methods psychologist
use in their science and practice. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

Advanced Placement Human Geography
18 weeks/1 credit
Accelerated in rigor and pace, this course serves as an introduction to geography as the science of location, with emphasis
on spatial patterns of human activities. The concepts of population, cultural patterns and processes, political organization of
space, agriculture and rural land use, industrialization and economic development, cities and urban land use form the core
of the course. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course

Advanced Placement European History
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: World History
Accelerated in rigor and pace, this course is the equivalent of a freshman college Western Civilization survey course which
begins with the Renaissance and ends with present day. All areas of history are covered including political, economic,
intellectual, cultural, social, and art history. Emphasis placed on analytical writing, class discussion, use of primary sources,
and critical reading. Students should possess strong reading and writing skills and be willing to devote time to study and the
completion of class assignments. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this
course.

                        *This course is offered at BJHS as a zero block course through Options Open. See your counselor
                        for more information.

Advanced Placement Seminar
18 weeks/1 credit
This class provides sustained practice of investigating issues from multiple perspectives and cultivates student writing
abilities so they can craft, communicate, and defend evidence-based arguments. Students are empowered to collect and
analyze information with accuracy and precision and are assessed through a team project and presentation, an individual
written essay and presentation, and a written exam. Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the
rigor of this course, in addition to a team project and presentation and an individual research-based essay and
presentation.

                                                                                51]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[Advanced Placement Research
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Advanced Placement Seminar
In this class, students develop the skills and discipline necessary to conduct independent research to produce and defend
a scholarly academic thesis. This second course in the AP Capstone experience allows students to explore deeply an
academic topic, problem, or issue of individual interest and through this inquiry, students design, plan, and conduct a year-
long mentored, research-based investigation. The course culminates in an academic thesis paper of approximately 5,000
words and a presentation, performance, or exhibition with an oral defense. An academic paper will be produced during
this class and student is required to present and defend his/her findings.

            Peer Helping (Student 2 Student)
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Based upon National Peer Helping Organization guidelines/application required
The mission of the Peer Helper Program in Madison City is to empower students to be successful academically, socially,
and emotionally; to recognize and resolve conflict; to value diversity; to be tobacco, alcohol and drug free; to be advocates
for positive change and healthy choices through learning to help and helping to learn. Peer Helpers will model and teach
these skills, values, and character traits to their peers through a collaborative classroom setting as well as elementary
students in the community.

Student Aide
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Computer Application or BTA/counselor approval required
This class is for seniors only. Students will assist with clerical needs of the main office, guidance office, media center,
attendance office, principals’ offices, and others as assigned. Students will receive a grade and 1 credit. Workplace skills
such as filing, typing, and reception duties will be emphasized. Enrollment requires an application process and will be
limited. Selection will be based, in part, on good attendance and conduct. Students must have passed all parts of the
graduation exam to participate.

                Student Leadership
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Student Government Sponsor approval
The Leadership and Student Government course is a recommended course for all elected class and associated student
body officers. Non-elected students may apply and be accepted into the course. The students will be responsible for school
wide activities, fundraisers, service projects and assemblies, with an emphasis on event planning and information
dissemination required to build community and create a positive educational environment. The overall objective of the course
is to facilitate the process of being effective leaders who support their educational community. School membership
requirements for the State, Southern Association and National Associations of Student Councils will be maintained and
members will compete at some or all of these levels at the respective conferences. Students who wish to develop the
following skills are encouraged to apply for the Student Leadership course:
*Develop leadership skills
*Prepare students to take leadership roles in the school and community
*Promote good citizenship and service

                        *This course is available zero block through the Options Open courses. See your counselor for
                        more information.

                                                                                52]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[SPECIAL SERVICES COURSES

For students served by Individual Education Plans (IEP) pursuing the Essentials/Life Skills Pathway

Number   Course                                   Credit
 700005    English Essentials 9                      1.0
 700006    English Essentials 10                     1.0
 700007    English Essentials 11                     1.0
 700008    English Essentials 12                     1.0
 700016    Algebraic Essentials A                    1.0
 700017    Algebraic Essentials B                    1.0
 700018    Geometry Essentials A                     1.0
 700019    Geometry Essentials B                     1.0
 700021    Life Skills Sci I / Physical Science      1.0
 700022    Life Skills Sci II / Biology              1.0
 700023    Life Skills Sci III / Earth and Space     1.0
 700024    Life Skills Sci IV / Environ Science      1.0
 700031    World History for Living                  1.0
 700032    US History for Living 10                  1.0
 700033    US History for Living 11                  1.0
 700034    Economics for Living                      0.5
 700035    U.S. Government for Living                0.5

 200061               SPECIAL SERVICES ELECTIVES     1.0
 210033                                              1.0
 600301    Reading Intervention                      1.0
 600302    Math Intervention                         1.0
 400016    Transitional Services I                   1.0
           Transitional Services Elective
           Workforce Essentials I

SPECIAL SERVICES

English Essentials 9
English Essentials 10
English Essentials 11
English Essentials 12
18 weeks each/1 credit each
This course is designed to provide a practical knowledge of reading, literature, writing and language, research and inquiry,
and oral and visual communication. They are designed to equip students with the skills necessary for employment and
independent living.

Algebraic Essentials A
18 weeks/1 credit
These courses provide students with foundational skills identified in the Algebra I course. The courses include essential
concepts to equip students with the algebra skills necessary for employment and independent living.

Algebraic Essentials B
18 weeks/1 credit
These courses provide students with foundational skills identified in the Algebra I course. The courses include essential
concepts to equip students with the algebra skills necessary for employment and independent living.

Geometry Essentials A
18 weeks/1 credit
These courses provide students with foundational skills identified in the Geometry course. The courses include essential
concepts to equip students with the geometry skills necessary for employment and independent living.

         53]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[Geometry Essentials B
18 weeks/1 credit
These courses provide students with foundational skills identified in the Geometry course. The courses include essential
concepts to equip students with the geometry skills necessary for employment and independent living.

LS Science I / Physical Science
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is designed to provide students with a practical knowledge of physical science including scientific process and
application skills; the periodic table; solutions; bonding; chemical formulas; physical and chemical changes; gravitational,
electromagnetic, and nuclear forces; motion; energy; energy transformation; electricity and magnetism; nuclear science;
and metric units.

LS Science II / Biology
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is designed to provide students with a practical knowledge of biology including scientific process and
application skills, cell processes, cell theory, photosynthesis and cellular respiration, genetics, classification, plants,
animals, ecology, and biogeochemical cycles.

LS Science III / Earth and Space
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is designed to provide students with a practical knowledge of earth and space science including scientific
process and application skills; energy in the Earth system; weather; seasons; theories for origin and age of the universe;
stars, pulsars, quasars, black holes, and galaxies; earth and space scientists; and space exploration.

LS Science IV / Environmental Science
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is designed to provide students with a practical knowledge of environmental science including scientific
process and application skills, natural and human impact on the environment, carrying capacity, renewable and
nonrenewable energy resources, properties and importance of water, land use practices, and composition and erosion of
soil.

World History for Living 10
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is a study of world history from 1500 to the present. Students are able to apply and utilize their knowledge to
develop informed opinions about issues such as the quest for peace, human rights, trade, global ecology, and the impact
each has on everyday life situations.

US History for Living 10
18 weeks/1 credit
This course follows a chronological study of major events, issues, movements, leaders, and groups of people of the United
States through Reconstruction from a national and Alabama perspective.

US History for Living 11
18 weeks/1 credit
This course begins with the post-Reconstruction United States and its shift into a more industrialized society and continues
through the twentieth century to the present.

Economics for Living
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is a one-semester course that focuses on the functions and institutions of modern-day economic systems and
theory. Students gain skills that will enable them to anticipate changes in economic conditions and how to adjust to the
changes to improve their lives and their communities.

US Government for Living
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is a one-semester course that focuses on the origins, structure, and functions of government at all levels. It
also includes a detailed study of the constitution of the United States and its provisions.

                                                                                54]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[SPECIAL SERVICES ELECTIVES

Transition Services I
18 weeks/1 credit
This course will prepare students to become self-advocates, participate in postsecondary education and/or training to gain
meaningful employment, and support community participation as they plan for life after high school.
Transition Services Elective
18 weeks/1 credit
This course focuses students - in community-based instruction, pre-vocational experience, and community integration
development.
Workforce Essentials I
18 weeks/1 credit
A one-credit course that provides students with higher-level academic and occupational skills that are transferable across
jobs and occupational areas. Emphasis is placed on career development and employment.

Other requirements for students pursuing the Essentials/Life Skills Pathway (24 credits)

     • Cooperative Education Seminar (COOP) / Work-based experience will be required for any students with
          disabilities earning core credits through Essentials / Life Skills courses (formerly known as AOD courses). Each
          student must complete a minimum of 140 hours of a documented, successful, independent, paid apprenticeship
          experience or unpaid internship experience.

     • 2 CTE courses (in sequence) and Workforce Essentials is concurrent/pre-requisite to Cooperative Education
          Seminar (COOP).

     • Career Preparedness Course (Computer Applications or Financial Literacy)
     • All Essentials/Life Skills credits shall comply with the current curriculum guides designated for Essentials/Life

          Skills course implementation and aligned with the Alabama Course of Study:
          http://alex.state.al.us/specialed/curriculum.html
     • Required to take the appropriate EOC in the content area. Substitute Essentials Pathway EOCs will be offered
          beginning with the 2015-2016 school year.

          Core classes for the Essentials Pathway will be taught in a collaborative/inclusive setting.

                                                                                55]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[SPECIAL SERVICES COURSES

For students served by Individual Education Plans (IEP) on the Extended Standards Pathway

Number  Course                                     Credit

600419  AAS: Reading-9                                     1.0

600420  AAS: Reading-10                                    1.0

600421  AAS: Reading-11                                    1.0

600422  AAS: Reading-12                                    1.0

600439  AAS: English Language Arts-9                       1.0

600440  AAS: English Language Arts-10                      1.0

600441  AAS: English Language Arts-11                      1.0

600442  AAS: English Language Arts-12                      1.0

600459  AAS: Mathematics-9                                 1.0

600460  AAS: Mathematics-10                                1.0

600461  AAS: Mathematics-11                                1.0

600462  AAS: Mathematics-12                                1.0

600479  AAS: Science-9                                     1.0

600480  AAS: Science-10                                    1.0

600481  AAS: Science-11                                    1.0

600482  AAS: Science-12                                    1.0

600499  AAS: Social Studies-9                              1.0

600500  AAS: Social Studies-10                             1.0

600501  AAS: Social Studies-11                             1.0

600502  AAS: Social Studies-12                             1.0

                SPECIAL SERVICES ELECTIVE COURSES

600512  AAS: Life Skills-9                                 1.0

600513  AAS: Life Skills-10                                1.0

600514  AAS: Life Skills-11                                1.0

600515  AAS: Life Skills-12                                1.0

600521  AAS: Pre-Vocational-9                              1.0

600522  AAS: Pre-Vocational-10                             1.0

600523  AAS: Pre-Vocational-11                             1.0

600524  AAS: Pre-Vocational-12                             1.0

600531  AAS: Vocational-9                                  1.0

600532  AAS: Vocational-10                                 1.0

600533  AAS: Vocational-11                                 1.0

600534  AAS: Vocational-12                                 1.0

600541  AAS: Community Based Instruction-9                 1.0

600542  AAS: Community Based Instruction-10                1.0

600543  AAS: Community Based Instruction-11                1.0

600544  AAS: Community Based Instruction-12                1.0

600551  AAS: Elective-9                                    1.0

600552  AAS: Elective-10                                   1.0

600553  AAS: Elective-11                                   1.0

600554  AAS: Elective-12                                   1.0

600001  Adaptive Physical Education                        1.0

  Courses above are for students with significant cognitive disabilities earning core credit through Alternate Achievement Standards
(AAS), which are aligned with the Alabama Course of Study, and being assessed through the Alabama Alternate Assessment (AAA).

                                       56]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[WORLD LANGUAGES

                   SPECIAL SERVICES COURSES

Number                 Course  Credit           Fee  AP Exam Fee

270023  French 1               1.0 $20                 Exam Fee
270024
270025  French 2               1.0 $20                 Exam Fee
270026                                                 Exam Fee
270027  French 3 Honors        1.0 $20
270153                                                 Exam Fee
270154  French 4 PreAP         1.0 $20
270155                                                 Exam Fee
270156  AP French Language     1.0
270157
270158  Spanish 1              1.0 $20
270043
270044  Spanish 2              1.0 $20
270045
270046  Spanish 3 Honors       1.0 $20
270047
270111  Spanish 4 PreAP        1.0 $20
270112
270113  AP Spanish Language    1.0
270114
270115  AP Spanish Literature  1.0 $20

        German 1               1.0 $20

        German 2               1.0 $20

        German 3 Honors        1.0 $20

        German 4 PreAP         1.0 $20

        AP German Language     1.0

        Latin 1                1.0 $20

        Latin 2                1.0 $20

        Latin 3                1.0 $20

        Latin 4 PreAP          1.0 $25

        AP Latin               1.0 $25

WORLD LANGUAGES

Successful completion of two levels of the same world language counts towards the Advanced Academic Diploma
Endorsement and the Madison City Seal of Academic Distinction. All courses are taught striving towards 90% or more in
the target language as is recommended by the American Council on the Teaching of Foreign Languages. For a classical
language, such as Latin, this refers to an emphasis on reading in the target language.

Level I Latin
18 weeks/1 credit
This course is structured around the Cambridge Latin series, which guides students through the experiences of ancient
Roman life by reading stories in Latin at the novice level. Students will have the opportunity to explore many of aspects of
ancient culture, such as urban life, entertainment, mythology, gender and social issues, and government. Students will
connect their own language and culture to Latin through vocabulary building and cultural analysis.

Level I French, German, Spanish
18 weeks/1 credit
This course focuses on the language learner's ability to communicate about topics relating to themselves, such as self-
description, basic needs, daily activities, preferences, everyday conversation, family, and friends. Students will read, listen
to, speak, and write the target language at the novice level. Students will explore various aspects of target culture through
authentic texts and speech, visuals, and hands-on learning.

Level II Latin
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level I Latin
In this course, students will continue with the Cambridge Latin series. Students will read Latin stories to develop a deeper
connection with vocabulary and grammar that will help them to better understand both Latin and English. Students will learn
about life across the Roman Empire and its provinces, including Britain, Egypt, and Carthage, and about the development
of the Roman civilization beginning with the founding of Rome stretching into the rise and fall of the Roman Empire. A few
passages from Roman authors, such as Vergil and Catullus, will be introduced, so that students will begin to have exposure
to authentic Latin texts.

                                                                                57]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[Level II French, German, Spanish
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level I
This course expands on the language learner's ability to communicate about topics that connect them to their immediate
environment, such as describing their place of residence, travel plans and experiences, health and lifestyle, and giving
opinions. Students will interpret, speak, and write in the target language at the novice-high to intermediate-low level,
particularly in the past tense. Students will continue to engage in gaining knowledge about the customs and people of the
target culture and to participate in real-world language experiences.

Level III Latin
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level II Latin
Honors Credit Awarded
Prose, poetry, and stories that center on Rome itself are at the heart of this course. Students will survey a variety of authors
of Latin literature, such as Pliny, Catullus, Martial, Ovid, Cicero, and Livy, and others per student request, as well as more
recently composed pieces from the realms of music, children’s literature, and philosophy. The course provides students the
opportunity to explore the impact that Roman society has had and continues to have on the world today, for example in the
world of politics, warfare, medicine, science, law, and the arts.

Level III French, German, Spanish
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level II
Honors Credit Awarded
This course strengthens the language learner’s ability to actively interpret the target language and produce language
independently while working with topics that connect to the countries and domains of the target language. Students will read
and discuss longer pieces of authentic literature at the intermediate-mid level. Students will learn to express themselves in
the target language, in that they will give and explain their opinions, describe future plans, hopes, and worries, and provide
explanation and clarification in conversation. Students will dig deeper into local and regional cultural products, practices,
and perspectives, both current and historical.

Level IV Pre-AP Latin
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level III Latin
Honors Credit Awarded
This course will have students read either selections of Vergil’s Aeneid, which explores the Trojan War and founding of
Rome, or selections of the Commentarii De Bello Gallico, written by one of the most famous politicians of all time - Julius
Caesar. Caesar will be read during even years, and Vergil will be read in the odd years. In addition, students will gain
experience with other authors of Latin prose and poetry. Students will analyze and discuss set passages, which will
prepare them for the AP Latin exam. Students will compose essays in English that demonstrate their understanding of
Latin texts. Students will also connect to the people in the texts through themes such as nationalism, politics, and cultural
values.

Level IV PreAP French, German, Spanish
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level III
Honors Credit Awarded
This course continues to provide the language learner an environment in which to interact with the target language at the
intermediate mid-high level in preparation for entrance into the Advanced Placement course. Students will participate in
frequent conversations, write compositions, read literary works, and discuss and/or summarize in the target language.
Students will examine topics, such as current events, global and social issues, and everyday life within the target culture.
Students will begin building more complex language structures and deepening vocabulary knowledge.

                                                                                58]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[Level V Advanced Placement Latin
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level IV PreAP Latin
In this course, students will read selections of the Latin author that were not read in Latin IV, i.e. Vergil or Caesar. As
students read and analyze the new set of texts, they will re-read and review the previous author, so that they can compose
essays in English that compare and contrast themes found in both, as well as various other poetry and prose authors.
Students will explore ancient Roman perspectives and cultural products and practices through these authentic texts.
Participation in national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.
Level V Advanced Placement French Language, Spanish Language, German Language
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level IV PreAP
This course is designed as a third year college level comprehensive course which includes 6 global themes: Beauty and
Aesthetics, Families and Communities, Person and Public Identities, Contemporary Life, Global Challenges and Science
and Technology. As directed by AP College Board these themes are structured to allow students opportunities to practice
interpersonal, interpretive, and presentational communicative skills. In addition students are expected to compare and /or
contrast as well as synthesize ideas and concepts within the target language culture and their own. Fluidity in listening,
reading, writing and speaking skills; the cornerstone of language acquisition is the goal of this course. The course is
conducted exclusively by both students and teachers in the target language Participation in national AP test is a
mandatory component in the rigor of this course.
Advanced Placement Spanish Literature
18 weeks/1 credit
Prerequisite: Level IV PreAP
This course is comparable to a third-year college introduction to Hispanic literature course. It is based on a required
reading list. The works on the list are of literary significance and represent various historical periods, literary movements,
genres, geographic areas, and population groups within the Spanish-speaking world. The objective of the course is to help
you interpret and analyze literature in Spanish. The course will be taught in the target language. Some works will contain
mature content matter. Students will also study culture, grammatical concepts, write compositions, analyze works, and
lead literary discussion groups. Advanced Placement Spanish V is not a prerequisite for this course. Participation in
national AP test is a mandatory component in the rigor of this course.

                                                                                59]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[2017
2018

                 REGISTRATION
                     FORMS

                                                    60]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[Bob Jones High School Registration Information Timeline

                                   Rising 12th grade students – Cohort 2018
                                   Rising 11th grade students – Cohort 2019
                                   Rising 10th grade students – Cohort 2020
                                   Rising 9th grade students – Cohort 2021

Feb 1-29       Students log on to school network and INOW during 2nd block. This process
               is required for students to register for classes online through INOW.

March 6        Students receive BJHS registration packet

March 7        Patriot Expedition - Field Trip/Tour of Bob Jones HS for Cohort 2021

               Curriculum Fair: 5:00-7:00 p.m. (Opportunity to learn about the course
               offerings) BJHS Central Commons Area

               Advanced Placement (AP) Meetings 5:30 p.m. & 6:30 p.m.
               (Informational) BJHS Media Center

               Rising 9th Grade Meetings 5:00 p.m. & 6:00 p.m. (New students welcome)
               BJHS Patriot Hall

March 12 – 16  SPRING BREAK – No school

March 20 - 24  Parent/Counselor 20 Minute Appointments
March 25 - 31  BJHS: Rising grades 10th -12th – Mrs. Diana Barry 256-772-2547 ext. 80366
March 29 -31   DMS: Rising 9thgrade – Mrs. Kelle Moody 256-837-3735 ext. 82126
               BJHS students will use INOW to enter course requests and complete the
               course request form located in the registration packet
               (Directions on BJHS website)

               DMS rising 9th grade students use INOW to enter course requests at
               school and turn in registration forms to Mrs. Kelle Moody at DMS

March 31       BJHS course request forms and additional forms (from Registration
               Packet) needed signed by parent and turned in to 2nd block teacher
               Last Day for Student Request Changes

August 2       Open House, 6pm-8pm

               Students are requesting courses for both Fall 2017 AND Spring 2018.

                   Request courses and alternate courses carefully as there are
          no changes to either requests or schedules after March 31, 2017 deadline.

                                    61]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[2017-2018 MADISON CITY SCHOOLS REGISTRATION INFORMATION
                           Rising 12th grade students – Cohort 2018
                           Rising 11th grade students – Cohort 2019
                           Rising 10th grade students – Cohort 2020
                           Rising 9th grade students – Cohort 2021

February 22nd  Flight of the JETS: Tour of James Clemens High School for Cohort 2021

March 1st      INOW Login Check: Students verify logins to the school network and INOW
March 6th      during Jet Advisory.

March 6th      Distribution of 2017-2018 Registration Packet: Students will
               receive the registration packet and information. The 2017-2018 Curriculum
March 6th -    Catalog will be on the school and district website prior to this day. Students will
March 10th     complete and turn into guidance the Course Request Form and four-year plan
               located at the back of the registration packet to finalize the registration process.
March 8th -
March 9th      Curriculum Fair: 5:00pm-7:00pm
March 6th -
March 24th     Advanced Placement (AP) Informational Meeting:
March 24th     Auditorium: 5:30pm
August 3rd
               Registration Informational Meeting: Rising and New Jets
               Auditorium: 6:15pm

               Rising Senior Week: Seniors can come to the guidance area to
               schedule an appointment to meet with their counselors (if needed). All students
               can schedule an appointment with their counselor at any time, but this week’s
               appointments with rising seniors will be taken first.

               Cohort 2021 Small Group Meetings: Counselors go to LMS to
               assist in registration

               Course Request Submissions: INOW opens to enter course
               requests from home/school (Directions on school website)

               Last Day for Student Schedule Requests:
               Signed registration forms due to counseling office

               Open House, 6pm-8pm

                                                    62]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[Madison City Schools
            Advanced Placement Agreement 2017-2018

Last Name:  First Name:                                                        MI:

Student Cell#: _____________________________________Student E-Mail___________________________________

Classification: 12th 11th 10th 9th

Statement of Accountability:
I understand that Advanced Placement (AP) classes are the most rigorous courses offered at the high school
level. I also understand that college-level work will be assigned and expected of me. I am electing to take the
challenge of an AP class and will work to meet the challenge. I have been advised about the expectations and
rigor of AP classes by one or more of the following individuals: an AP teacher, my counselor, the AP coordinator,
and/or have attended the AP information session for the 2017-2018 school year. I am committed to completing
the AP courses during the 2017-2018 school year for which I have registered.

I am currently registered for the following AP courses:
               1. 5.

               2. 6.

               3. 7.

               4. 8.

By signing this agreement, I understand and agree to the following conditions and expectations involved in
taking one or more AP class in Madison City Schools:

     • I will remain enrolled in the class for the duration of the course. No requests for schedule changes will
          be honored after March 24th, 2017 (JCHS) / March 31st, 2017 (BJHS).

     • I understand the summer commitments of the class, and I will be prepared to turn in completed
          summer work assignments upon the teacher’s request.

     • I will give every assignment my best effort and will respect and adhere to due dates.
     • I understand that I am responsible for the course fee as well as the cost of taking the AP exam(s).
     • I understand that I am required to take the National AP Exam as part of the course curriculum

I affirm that I have read, understand, and agree to the stipulations of this agreement.

___________________________________________      ____________

                            Student Signature          Date

___________________________________________      ____________

                      Parent/Guardian Signature        Date

*This agreement should be completed and turned in with your registration form

            63]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[MADISON CITY SCHOOLS
                                  DUAL ENROLLMENT PROGRAM AGREEMENT

Registration Course Numbers:
802111 Dual Enrollment (fall semester)
802111 Dual Enrollment (spring semester)

Student will take two classes in MADISON CITY (Bob Jones or James Clemens) for ½ of the school day and enroll in a
college course at either Calhoun Community College or UAH for the other ½ of the school day. The college course grade
is included in the MADISON CITY GPA.

Dual enrollment is under review. The weight associated with dual enrollment classes and the college class (or
combination of classes) needed to earn one Carnegie unit are under review. Students who enroll in Dual Enrollment
courses are responsible for verifying the high school credit and applicable GPA calculation that will be received for the
course. More information will be available on dual enrollment before the curriculum fairs.

*Upon successful completion of the course, high school counselors will ensure the credit is reflected on both the high
school and college transcript (per SDE).

This option may be for one or both semesters in either the morning or afternoon.

     1. Must have a cumulative G.P.A. of 3.0 or higher
     2. Must have an ACT composite score of 20 or higher
     3. Must be able to pay tuition for 3 college credit hours
     4. Must provide own transportation
     5. Requires completion of this agreement

I give permission for ___________________________________ to participate in the Dual Enrollment Program. I
have read and understand the above information. I also understand that my student must provide his/her own
transportation. By signing below, I give permission for my student to leave school early and drive to a college or
university for dual enrollment purposes.

Parent/Guardian Signature: ________________________________ Date: ____________

Student Signature: ______________________________________ Date: _____________

*This agreement should be completed and turned in with your 2017-2018 registration forms. Registration information must
be completed and submitted to the counseling office no later than March 24, 2017 (JCHS) or March 31. 2017 (BJHS).

        FOR OFFICE USE ONLY

        Date returned: ____________________

        Student GPA: ____________________

        Student ACT: ____________________

        College Course_____________________________________ State Number __________________

        College Course _____________________________________ State Number __________________
        *Dual Enrollment course(s) must be entered in INOW to reflect the corresponding state course code(s).
        These numbers begin in the 90000.

                                                                                64]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[EARLY OR MIDYEAR COMPLETION

Students may complete their course work for graduation early from Madison City Schools by meeting all requirements for
an Alabama Diploma as described in the Alabama Administrative Code 290-030-010-.6 (11) and when the conditions
listed below are met. Students may also accelerate their program of studies by enrolling in summer school and dual
enrollment at a postsecondary institution.

     A. Students must submit the Early or Midyear Completion form with a parent’s signature no later than the semester
          prior to midyear completion

     B. Students who plan to complete early must follow course sequence/prerequisites.
     C. Students who plan to complete early will not be given preferential treatment in registration and course selection.
     D. Students who plan to accelerate their program of studies for the purpose of early completion may do so if space is

          available in classes after grade level students have completed registration.
     E. Students who complete graduation requirements early will not be permitted to remain at school during the regular

          school day. However, they may return to school for senior activities and after school activities provided they
          remain in good standing with the school and follow the local school procedures for returning to the campus.
     F. A student must be a full time student to be eligible to participate in extracurricular activities. Therefore, a student
          who completes graduation requirements early will not be eligible for extracurricular activities.
     G. Students who complete graduation requirements early will receive their diplomas at the regularly scheduled
          graduation ceremony.

Students who complete their coursework early are responsible for making contact with school officials concerning
graduation, senior events, award ceremonies, etc. Students/Parents must also be aware that if students begin taking
college courses immediately after they finish their classes in December, some colleges/universities may deem them
ineligible for Freshman Scholarships.

I request that ___________________________________ be allowed to pursue mid-year completion at the end of
December of their senior year. By signing below, I acknowledge that I have read and understand the above
information.
I request that ___________________________________ be allowed to graduate at the end of his/her next school
year (one year early). By signing below, I acknowledge that I have read and understand the above information.
Parent/Guardian Signature: ___________________________________ Date: ____________

Student Signature: ___________________________________________ Date: ____________

*This agreement should be completed and turned in with your registration form

                                                                                65]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[CREDIT RECOVERY PROGRAM

The Madison City Schools (MCS) Credit Recovery Program is designed to offer students who have received failing grades
in required core courses an opportunity to recover the lost credit through computer-based instruction targeting specific
knowledge and skill deficits instead of requiring the students to repeat the entire course. Students must meet eligibility
requirements to apply.

Student Eligibility, Admission and Removal:
     • Any student who has failed one or more core courses listed below during the 9th - 12th grade years may apply for
          admission.

     • Student, parent or guardian, counselor and administrator must sign the MADISON CITY Contract for Success.
     • Payment will be required upon registration.
     • If the final grade earned in a core course required for graduation was between 50% - 64%, then a series of

          diagnostic tests will determine the specific standards to be mastered to obtain credit.

     • If the final grade earned in a core course required for graduation was between 0% - 49%, then the student may
          attend the Credit Recovery program, but all standards for the failed course will be assigned for remediation.

     • Satisfactory completion of the course will result in a final grade of 70.
     • Credits recovered will be denoted on the transcript with a CR and the previously earned failing grade will remain

          on the transcript and both will be calculated into the overall Grade Point Average.

     • Students may be removed from the Credit Recovery program at the discretion of the administrator supervising the
          program for circumstances involving serious or repeated misbehavior or failure to make adequate progress
          towards meeting remediation requirements.

     • Student who do not qualify for Credit Recovery or cannot complete a Credit Recovery program under these
          guidelines will be required to repeat the failed course covering all applicable standards and attending the total
          number of required instructional hours.

     • Student must attend a minimum of 8 hours of class.
     • Credit Recovery coursework is not approved for eligibility through the NCAA clearinghouse.

Dates: Available each semester (See counselor for more information)

     • Dates and times vary per school. Students can get specific information from their guidance counselor.
     • Program is individualized and completion times will vary per student. Students are required to attend until all

          course requirements are complete.

Registration: On-going throughout semester

     • Seats are limited and each session will have a maximum of 25 students. As students complete, seats will open
          and filled on a first come first serve basis.

Cost: $275 per 1.0 credit OR $150 per 0.5 credit course payable in cash or check upon registration

Courses Offered:  Algebra IA  Physical Science          World History
English 9         Algebra IB
English 10        Algebra I   Biology Early             US History
English 11        Geometry A
English 12        Geometry B  Chemistry I               Modern US History

                              Physics                   Economics (0.5 credit)

                              Environmental Science US Government (0.5 credit)

                              Geometry                  Earth and Space Science

                              Algebraic Connections

                              Algebra II with Trig

                                                    66]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[2017-2018                            Course Request Form                           COHORT 2021

                                                                                                       Rising 9th Grade

Please fill out this form carefully. These choices will become your class schedule for Fall 2017 and Spring 2018.

Last Name:                                           First Name:                                        MI: ___________

Student School E-Mail:                                            Student Cell #:

Directions: Please check ( ) the box to the LEFT of your choice.

             English Core – ( ) Select 1                          Composition /Career Prep - ( ) Select 1

Course #                Course Name               credit           Course #                Course Name           credit
                                                                  200032
200005 English Gr 9                                 1                              Composition &                   1
                                                    1                              Career Prep A
                                                    1
200007aa English Gr 9 PreAP                                       200032ac Comp & Career Prep B

                                                                                                                   1

300001aa ELL English

                                                                                  *Comp &                          1
                                                                  802200ak Career Prep A Online

             Math Core - ( ) Select 1                                             *Comp &
                                                                  802200an Career Prep B Online
Course #              Course Name                 credit                                                           1

210008 &     Algebra IA &                           2         * Online Class – In addition to 8 classes at BJHS. All
210009       Algebra 1B                             2         work will be completed outside the regular school day.
                                                    1
210013 & Geometry A &                                             Science Core – ( ) Select 1
210014 Geometry B

210010 Geometry                                                   Course #         Course Name                   credit

                                                                  220051 Physical Science                          1
                                                                                                                   1
210011aa Geom PreAP                               1               220011 Biology                                   1

210012aa GeomPreAPMT (math team) 1                                220013aa Biology, PreAP

             Elective and World Language Choices                  Social Science Core – ( ) Select 1

Course #     Elective Course Name Credits                         Course #         Course Name                   credit

                                                  1               230013 World History 1500-P                      1

                                                  1               230027           World History AP                1

                                                  1                                (summer assignment required)

Fill in all Alternate Choices in order of

preference.

Course #                Alternate Course Name                 All students will be scheduled for a total of

                                                              8 classes/credits for the entire school year.

                                                                      4 classes in the FALL semester
                                                                     4 classes in the SPRING semester

                                                          67]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[The following courses are open to rising 9th graders.            Physical Education Athletic Teams- **Tryout Required

        Fine Arts - ** requires attendance at summer band camp

 280071        Theatre 1 (audition required for levels above 1)  240002    Life PE-1 Credit
 280079        TheaDes/Tech
 280093        Visual Arts 1                                     240002ad/240002an LIFE JV Football Fall/Spring - 2 credits
 280051        Vocal I
 280053        Vocal II                                          240002ah  **LIFE Cheerleading Fall
 280031aa      **Inst Level I - Marching Band
 280031ab      **Inst Level I - Comp Mar Band                    240002am/240002bi LIFE Wrestling Fall/Spring – 2 credits
280037         (direct)Insd)approval)                                                     iNDOOR
 280037aa      **Inst Level IV - Perc MB Fall
 280033aa      Indoor Drumline (Spring)                          240002af/240002ao **LIFE Baseball Boys Fall/Spring- 2 credits
 280035aa      Inst Level II - Concert Band
 280011        Inst Level III - Wind Ensemble (audition)         240002al/240002ap **LIFE Basketball Boys Fall/Spring-2 credits
 280012        Life Dance I (color guard) Fall
               Life Dance II (dance team) Fall                   240002ab/240002as **LIFE Basketball Girls Fall/Spring- 2 credits
 210015
 210017                   Math                                   240002aj  LIFE Golf Boys & Girls Spring
 210017aa      Algebraic Connections
 210017ab      Algebra 2/Trig                                    240002aq  **LIFE Softball Spring
               Algebra 2/ Trig Pre-AP
 480001        Algebra 2/Trig Pre-AP Math Team                   240002ak  LIFE Tennis Girls & Boys Spring
 480022    JROTC - May count as a PE credit
               Leadership & Aviation Hist. Part I                240002bc  LIFE Track Spring – 5th Block
 270023        Leadership & Aviation Hist. Part II
270024                                                           240002az  **LIFE Soccer Spring – 5th Block
 270025           World Languages
 270043        French 1                                          240002ba  LIFE Swim/Dive Fall – 5th Block
 270044        French 2
 270111        French 3 Honors                                   240002bb  LIFE Cross Country Fall – 5th Block
 270112        German 1
 270153        German 2                                                    Miscellaneous
 270154        Latin 1
270155         Latin 2                                           460009    Education and Training
               Spanish 1
               Spanish 2                                         560015    Introduction to Engineering Design
               Spanish 3 Honors
                                                                 490042    Principles of Biomedical Sciences

                                                                 510004    Family and Consumer Science

                                                                 510041    Fashion

                                                                 450006    Business Technology Applications (BTA)

                                                                 520015    Software Development (C Programming)

                                                                 200033    Creative Writing

                                                                 410016    Multimedia Design
                                                                 520038    Foundations of Informational Security
                                                                           A(CPybPesryscehcoulorigtyyI)
                                                                 230072

                                                                 230062    AP Human Geography

                                                                 260007    AP Computer Science Principles
                                                                 412101    (Application required)
                                                                           Building Science NCCER #1

                                                                 420057    Landscape Design & Mgmt.

By signing, we understand that there are NO changes to course requests or schedules after March 31, 2017.

Student Signature: ____________________________________ Parent Signature: ______________________________________________
Parent Cell Phone: ___________________________________ Parent Email: _________________________________________________

                                                                                  68]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[Bob Jones High School    Course Request Form 2017-18                                               Circle Graduation COHORT

                                                                                                   2018 2019 2020

Last Name: _____________________________________ First Name: _______________________MI: ________

Student Cell:                         Student E-Mail:

Please fill out this form with care. These choices will become your schedule for 2017-2018.
Write the full course # and course name found in the course list included in registration packet.

Core Area      Course #                   Course Name                                                               # Credit
 English

   Math

 Science
Social Sci.

ELECTIVES & WORLD LANGUAGES: If you select a 0.5 credit class, you must select another 0.5 credit to pair with it.

Course #                              Course Name                                                                   # Credit

                                                       TOTAL CREDITS Requested = 8

ALTERNATES: List alternates in priority order. If you select a 0.5 credit class, you must select another 0.5 credit to pair with it.
Remember you are not guaranteed every elective request. This is why you must select alternate choices.

Course #                              Course Name                                                                   # Credit

Course #                 Course Name  You may take a block “off” in place of your Options Open class
                                      and must leave campus (Gr. 10 - 12). You must provide.
                                      transportation to and from campus.

                                       Which block do you want off (if any)?
                                       Example: 1st or 4th block/fall or spring

SUMMER SCHOOL PLANS?

                                      69]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[Students:

       • I have read the course catalog and understand the requirements for graduation for my cohortyear.

       • I have chosen my course requests for BOTH SEMESTERS for the 2017-2018 school year very carefully.

       • I have put alternate elective choices in priority order. I understand that I am not guaranteed all of my 1st choice
           electives.

       • I understand that there will be NO schedule changes after March 31, 2017, even if I change my mind over the
           summer.

       • I understand that I cannot drop an Honors or AP course once requested.

       • I have attached approval forms for courses that require approval, auditions or applications (if applicable).

       • I have also attached AP Agreement, Dual Enrollment, Work-Based Learning (Co-Op) and Early Completion

Student Signature:                                                        Date:

Parent/Guardian:

• I have read the course catalog and understand the requirements for graduation for my child’s cohort year.

• I have reviewed my child’s course selections for BOTH SEMESTERS for the 2017-2018 schoolyear.

• I approve the courses my child has requested for the 2017-2018 school year.

• I understand that there are NO schedule changes after March 31, 2017 even if my child changes his/her mind about
    a course.

• I understand that my child cannot drop an Honors or AP course once requested.

• I understand that I will be responsible for paying for all fees related to AP exams.

Parent Signature:                                                         Date::
___________________________________________                               ______________________

Parent E- Mail:                                                           Cell:
___________________________________________ Mmmail:                       _______________________

Four Year Plan                    9th Grade                   Grade 10    Grade 11                         Grade 12
                                  English 9                   English 10  English 11                       English 12
English Core (4 Credits)
Math Core (4 Credits)             World History               US History  US History 2  Govt/Econ
Algebra, Geometry, and Algebra 2                              Health
or Algebra 2/Trig                 Career Prep OR
Science Core (4 credits)          Career Prep B (only if Car
Biology and A Physical Science
Social Science (4 Credits)        Prep A has been
Elective Credits                  completed.)

Total                             88                                             88

                                                              70]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[Graduation Cohort                 2021 - 9th Grade

                      James Clemens High School 2017-2018 Course Request Form

   Please fill out this form with care. These choices will become your schedule for the 2017-2018 school year.

   Last Name:                                                                  First Name:

   Student E-Mail                                                              Student Cell#:

                   Please circle the box of your course choices. You must have a total of 8 credits.

                   English Core                                                                          Math Core

        Course #                      Course Name       Credits                       Course #                 Course Name  Credits
         200005                 English Grade 9           1                       210008/210009          Algebra 1A/B          2
         200007                 English Grade 9 PreAP     1                       210013/210014          Geometry A/B          2
         400025                 Career Prep               1                                              Geometry              1
   802200am                     Career Prep (online)      1                           210010             Geometry, PreAP       1
                                                                                      210012
       400027                   Career Prep B (only if   .5                                              Geometry, PreAP       1
                                                                                     210012aa            Math Team
                                Car Prep A has been

                                completed.)

   802200ae                     Career Prep B (online) .5

   Course #         Science Core                        Credits                   Course #     Social Science Core          Credits
   220011                                                  1                      230013                                       1
   220013                  Course Name                     1                      230027               Course Name             1
   220051          Biology                                 1                                   World History
                   Biology PreAP                                                               World History, AP
                   Physical Science

Elective Courses: In addition to your 4 required core selections, select additional core/or elective credits.
If you are requesting a course that requires an approval, an audition, or an application you must attach a course approval form to your request
form.

                        Elective Choices-                                                                Alternate Elective Choices-

                   Please select 4 elective choices                               Please select 4 elective choices. Remember you are NOT

                                                                                                 guaranteed every elective request.

   Course #                     Course Name             Credits                             This is why you must select alternate choices

1                                                                                           Alternate #   Alternate Name                   Credits

2                                                                              1

3                                                                              2

4                                                                              3

   World Language Elective Choice                                              4

   Course #                     Course Name             Credits                   World Language Alternate Elective Choice

1                                                                                           Alternate #   Alternate Name                   Credits

                                                                               1

Four Year Plan                               9th Grade           Grade 10                                Grade 11                      Grade 12
English Core (4 Credits)                     English 9           English 10                              English 11                    English 12

Math Core (4 Credits)            World History                   US History 1               US History 2                    Govt/Econ
Algebra,Geometry,andAlgebra2or   Career Prep OR                  Health
Science Core (4 credits)          Career Prep B (only if Car
Biology and A Physical Science
Social Science (4 Credits)        Prep A has been completed.)

 Elective Credits

Total 8 8 8 8
                                                                                 71]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[Additional courses are open to 9th graders.                          LIFE PE            Athletic Teams- Tryout Required
                              Fine Arts                              240002ad/240002an  LIFE JV Football/Football Spring- 2 credits
                                                                     240002ah           LIFE Cheerleading Fall
280071                Theatre 1                                      280011             Dance I (color guard/dance line)
280079                Technical Theatre                              280012             Dance II (competition dance team)
280032                Piano I                                        240002am           LIFE Wrestling
280093                Visual Arts 1                                  240002af/240002ao  LIFE Baseball Boys Fall/Spring- 2 credits
280051                Vocal I (Mixed Choir)                          240002al/240002ap  LIFE Basketball Boys Fall/Spring- 2 credits
280053                Vocal 2 (Treble Choir)                         240002ab/240002as  LIFE Basketball Girls Fall/Spring- 2 credits
280031aa              Marching Band (Fall)                           240002aj           LIFE Golf Boys and Girls /Spring
280031ab              Competition Marching Band (director approval)  240002aq/240002ao  LIFE Softball Fall/Spring- 2 credits
280037                Percussion Marching Band (Fall)                240002ak           LIFE Tennis Girls and Boys/Spring
280037aa              Spring Percussion (Spring)                     240002ba           LIFE Swim Fall
280033aa              Concert Band(Spring)                           240002bc           LIFE Track Fall/Spring
280035                Wind Ensemble (Spring-director approval)       240002az           LIFE Soccer Spring
280039aa              Guitar 1                                                          Physical Education

                                 Math

210015                Algebraic Connections                          240002             LIFE PE--1 Credit*
210017                Algebra 2/Trig                                 240002aa           LIFE PE-- .5 Credit
210017aa              Algebra 2/Trig PreAP
                                                                                         Miscellaneous
210017ab              Algebra 2/Trig PreAP Math Team
                                JROTC                                460009             Education and Training
480041                                                               560015             Introduction to Engineering Design
480042                Leadership Education and Training I (LETI)
                      Leadership and Training II (LETII)             200033             Creative Writing

                           World Languages                           510004             Family and Consumer Science
                                                                     260007
270023                French 1                                       430004             AP Computer Science Principles
270024                French 2                                                          NCCER Architecture, Construction,
270043                German 1                                       520015             Manufacturing
270044                German 2                                       230072             Software Development (C Programming)
270111                Latin 1                                        450006             AP Psychology
                                                                     440017             Business Technology Applications (BTA)
270112                Latin 2                                        230062             Introduction to Television Production
270153                Spanish 1                                      490024             AP Human Geography
270154                Spanish 2                                      490042             Orientation to Health Science
                                                                     520005             Principles of the Biomedical Sciences
270155                Spanish 3 Honors                               520038             IT Fundamentals
                                                                                        Foundations of Informational Security
                                                                                        (Cybersecurity I)

Ihavereadthecoursecatalogandunderstandtherequirements. Ihavereviewedthecourseselectionsandcompletedthe4-year plan. Iapprove thecourses
my childhas requested forthe2017-2018schoolyearandunderstandthat thereareNOschedule changes after March 24, 2017,even if mychild changes
his/her mind about a course. I understand that my child cannot drop an HonorsorAPcourseoncescheduled.

Student Signature                            Date                              Parent Signature

Parent Email Address                                                                                        Parent Cell #

                                                                     72]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[Graduation Cohort  2020/10th graders                2019/11th graders         2018/12th graders

                                              James Clemens High School

                                                              Cohorts 2018-2020 Course Request Form
      Tobecompletedbyrising10th,11th,and12th graders.Thesechoiceswillbecomeyourschedule forthe2017-2018school year. There will be NO

                                                              changes to your requests after March 24, 2017.

Last Name:                                               First Name:

StudentCell#:                                            Student E-Mail

For ALL course names, please write the full course name found in the course catalog.

    Core Area                                  Full Course Name                                           Credit

English

Math

Science
Social Studies

Elective Courses: In additionto your core selections above, select additional core/or elective credits. Remember you are NOT
guaranteed every elective request. This is why you must select alternate choices. If you select a 0.5 credit class, you must select another
0.5credit to equal 1.0credit.

                             World Language Elective Choices

If taking a world language(s), include your first choice below along with alternate language(s). If no world languages are to be taken, fill
in elective choices below in the next section.

      Course #  Course Name  Credits                         Alternate                 Alternate Name Credits

                                                                 #

12

                Elective Course: Full name of Course                            Teacher Signature if                                         Credit
                                                                                 approval is needed
1.

2.

3.

4.

5.

                                                                                       8 Total Credits                                       8.0

                   Elective Course Alternate Choices (please put in preference order)                     Credit
1.
2.
3.
4.
5.

*If you are requesting a course that requires approval, an audition or an application, you must have a teacher signature on your registration form. During

the scheduling process there may be conflicts between core courses and electives. Due to conflicts you are not guaranteed elective courses.

Additional Information:

Are youplanning to attend summerschool this summer? YES          N0

Summer School Course(s):

                                                         73]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[Students:

I have read the course catalog and understand the requirements for graduation for my cohort year.
I have chosen my course requests for BOTH SEMESTERS for the 2017-2018 school year very carefully.
I have put alternate elective choices in priority order. I understand that I am not guaranteed all of my 1st choice elective choices.
Iunderstand thattherewill be NO schedule changes after March 24, 2017,evenif Ichange my mind. This meansI maynotdropan Honors or AP class once scheduled.
Ihaveattachedapprovalformsforcoursesthatrequireapproval,auditionsorapplications(ifapplicable). Ihavealsoattached
DualEnrollment,earlycompletionorWork-BasedLearningpermissionforms(if applicable).

Student Signature:                                                                   Date:

Parent/Guardian:
Ihavereadthecoursecatalogandunderstandtherequirementsforgraduationformychild’scohortyear. Ihavereviewedboth
my child’s course selections and his/her 4-year plan.
I approve the courses my child has requested for the 2017-2018 school year.
IunderstandthatthereareNOschedulechangesafterMarch 24, 2017,evenifmychildchangeshis/hermind aboutacourse. Iunderstandthatmy
child cannot drop an Honors or AP course once scheduled.

 Parent Signature:                                                                   Date:
                                                                                     Cell Phone:
 Parent E-mail:
                                                          9th Grade      10th Grade             11th Grade       12th Grade
Four Year Plan                                       English 9       English 10             English 11      English 12
English- 4 Credits
Math-4credit -2017+ must haveAlgIIor                 World History   United States          United States   US Govt/Econ
AlgebraIIw/Trigorequivalent                                          History I              History II
Science- 4 credits -
Biology & a physical science + 2 more

Social Studies- 4 credits

Required elective courses:

LIFEPE(1), Health(0.5) ,CareerPrep (A & B)(1) Other
electives(3 credits)should befromFine Arts,Career
Tech,orWorldLanguages

Total Credits

                                                                     74]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[Madison City Schools
                ACCESS Virtual Learning Procedures

Background
The purpose of the Madison City Schools Virtual Option is to provide motivated, independent learners with engaging,
student-centered courses to meet each student’s educational needs in an online environment that will allow flexible,
individualized learning.

Law
Beginning with the 2016-2017 school year, State of Alabama Act 2015-89 requires that all school boards offer students in
grades 9-12 an online pathway for earning a high school diploma. A link to the full text of the law, passed April 28, 2015,
can be found in Appendix A. The law allows school boards to write their own policies and procedures to accommodate
their virtual school needs. The following encompasses Madison City Schools’ procedures regarding its virtual option.

Benefits
What are the benefits of the virtual option?

          • Instruction from certified teachers
          • No tuition and minimal fees*
          • Accredited diploma upon satisfying all Madison City Schools graduation requirements**
          • Flexible and personalized learning experiences
          • Individualized academic and career preparation plan
          • Self-pacing and opportunity for accelerated advancement
          • Early graduation available upon meeting eligibility criteria
          • Flexibility to pursue personal interests
          *Course work completed during summer term will require fees
          **See Appendix B for the Madison City Schools graduation requirements

Curriculum
The Madison City Schools Virtual Option uses the curriculum of ACCESS Virtual Learning, a program administered by
the Alabama State Department of Education. See Appendix A for a link to more details about online courses provided
through ACCESS. All course curricula are aligned to Alabama Courses of Study. Students also have the option of taking
some locally developed online courses taught by Madison City Schools teachers through Options Open. See Appendix A
for a link to further details about Options Open. Students intending to complete all graduation requirements through the
Virtual Option must meet the Madison City Schools Graduation requirements (See Appendix B).

Hours of Operation
The Madison City Schools Virtual Option operates on a standard semester system in accordance with the Madison City
School System’s approved academic calendar. Most classes are offered in a full year format or a “block” format. The
start and end date of ACCESS Virtual Learning classes (regardless of the format) is determined by the Alabama State
Department of Education and is closely aligned with the Madison City School System’s academic calendar.
For questions or technical support, the Madison City ACCESS Support Center can be contacted via phone (1-877-295-
0526 or 256-774-4609) or email (mcaccesshelp@madisoncity.k12.al.us) Monday through Friday between the hours of
8:00 am and 4:00 pm.

Attendance
Madison City Virtual Option students are required to abide by Madison City attendance policies and procedures.
Students fulfill attendance requirements by actively participating in the online course(s). If students are not up to date
with course work within five academic days, they are put on academic probation. Students will have two academic days
to rectify the situation. If a student does not stay up to date with coursework for an additional five academic days, he or
she will be put on academic probation again. The third occurrence, signaling the need for academic probation, warrants
withdrawal from the class.

Course Testing Schedule
Madison City Schools Virtual Option follows the ACCESS Virtual Learning testing procedure. All unit tests and semester
examinations must be taken in the physical presence of an ACCESS Virtual Learning facilitator or teacher. Students
must report to their zoned school to take assessments. Scores earned on exams that are not taken at an approved

                                                                            75]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[testing site with an ACCESS Virtual Learning facilitator or teacher are not valid. Students must provide their own
transportation to and from the testing site.

State Testing Schedule
Madison City Virtual School students are required to take all state-mandated assessments on site at their zoned school.
All 10th grade students take the PSAT in the fall semester and the ACT Aspire in the spring semester. All 11th grade
students take the ACT Plus Writing in the spring semester and have the option to take the PSAT during the fall semester.
Seniors take the ACT WorkKeys in the spring semester. Students must provide their own transportation to the testing
site. See Appendix A for a link to the state testing schedule.

Grades
The Madison City Schools Virtual Option will follow grading policies set forth by ACCESS. See Appendix A for a link with
more information about ACCESS procedures.

Weighting of Honors and AP Classes
ACCESS Virtual Learning Spanish 3, Spanish 4, German 3, French 3, Latin 3, and Precalculus courses will earn honors
weight. AP classes taken through ACCESS Virtual Learning will earn AP weight.

Course Progression
Students are required to progress through virtual option courses at a rate comparable to that of a traditional class.
Student athletes are required to maintain a traditional pace to follow NCAA/Alabama High School Athletic Association
rules. Students are permitted to work ahead of the standard course progression and finish courses early if they are not
an athlete.
Minimum Requirements to Remain Enrolled
The minimum requirements to remain enrolled in a Madison City School virtual option course are as follows:

     ● Live in the Madison City Schools zone
     ● Have a personal device (or access to a device) and maintain consistent, daily access to the Internet
     ● Maintain minimum GPA of 2.0 in all courses taken during the current academic year

    ● Maintain appropriate course progression as measured by the completion of weekly assignments, quizzes, and

          tests

    ● Remain in good standing as a student of Madison City Schools Virtual Option (see Appendix C for the
         Academic Integrity Agreement)

    ● Students with discipline infractions resulting in suspension or expulsion may be removed from the
         Madison City Schools Virtual Option

Failed Classes
If a student fails a Virtual Option course, the student can retake the course through summer school or credit recovery. If a
student fails a class and retakes the class in summer school, then, upon the successful completion of summer school,
the student’s GPA for the academic year just completed will be recalculated. If the student’s GPA is at least a 2.0, the
student is still on track for graduation, and he/she meets all other requirements and expectations of Madison City
Schools, then the student will be permitted to continue his/her enrollment in the Virtual Option.

Required Courses
Students are required to attempt a minimum of eight credits per school year. For student athletes, four of the eight credits
must be core classes (math, science, English, and social studies) unless the student athlete has accumulated more core
credits than is required for the student to remain on track for graduation. With parent permission, students may be
allowed to earn additional credits per year. Students should register for Virtual School Option courses during the spring
registration and submit the Virtual Option Registration Form by their zoned school’s registration deadline (See Appendix
D for the Virtual Option Registration Form).

Transportation
Any necessary transportation must be provided by parents/guardians or by the licensed virtual option student who has
submitted proper documentation in accordance with Madison City Schools transportation procedures.

Extracurricular Activities
Students enrolled in the Madison City Schools Virtual Option are eligible to participate in school-sponsored
extracurricular activities, including athletics.

                                                                               76]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[Virtual Options
                                   Helpful Links

Alabama Virtual Option State Law
         https://web.alsde.edu/legislativebills/2015Regular/SB0072_ENACTED.pdf

ACCESS Student Manual
         http://accessdl.state.al.us/content/Policy_Manual_for_Students

ACCESS Course List
         http://accessdl.state.al.us/sites/default/files/documents/10-30-15_Catalog_Fall15-Summer2016_Web-
         BasedCourses_0.pdf

Madison City Schools Options Open Program
         http://tinyurl.com/MCSOptionsOpen

Alabama State Testing Schedule
         http://data.madisoncity.k12.al.us/documents/Calendars/2015-
         2016%20%20state%20testing%20dates%20%20.pdf

                                                                               77]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[78]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[79]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[Virtual Option Agreement

                        Madison City Schools

                          Virtual Option Agreement

ACADEMIC INTEGRITY
The Academic Integrity Agreement of the Madison City Schools Virtual Option combines the existing
Academic Integrity Policy of ACCESS Virtual Learning with the additional requirements of the Madison City
School district.
ACCESS Virtual Learning
ACCESS Virtual Learning students must sign a commitment form attesting to academic integrity regarding
each of the following topics. If a student fails to abide by these policies, the student will be removed from the
course and will be subject to other consequences as determined by ACCESS Virtual Learning and local
school system administrators.
• All work must be completed by the student alone.
• Any collaboration among students must be pre-approved by the teacher.
• Cheating will not be allowed in any form. See Madison City Schools’ Board Policy CSC VIII C.
• Students will not allow others to copy their work.
• Content from the Internet will not be misused or misrepresented.
• Translators are prohibited in all Foreign Language ACCESS classes
All ACCESS Virtual Learning teachers utilize a variety of technologies to check student work for authenticity. If
an instructor confirms that a student has cheated in any manner, the student will be subject to consequences
determined by ACCESS Virtual Learning administrative staff, the distance learning teacher, and the local
school system, and will be subject to removal from the course with a failing grade.

                                                                               80]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[STUDENT AGREEMENT

I have read and understand the Madison City Schools Virtual Option Procedures and the Academic Integrity
Agreement. Failure to comply with those procedures or the following may result in dismissal from the Virtual
Option:

    1. All work submitted will by my own work.
    2. I will abide by all Madison City Schools Virtual Option and ACCESS Virtual Learning policies and

         procedures.
    3. I agree to take all course tests and examinations at my zoned school with an ACCESS Virtual

         Learning facilitator or teacher.
    4. I agree to take all Alabama mandated assessments as proctored examinations at my zoned school.
    5. I will complete all assignments and meet all deadlines.
    6. I will work cooperatively with my teacher and other students showing respect for all.

Student Name (print):_________________________________________________________

Student Signature:___________________________ Date: __________  _____

PARENT/GUARDIAN AGREEMENT

I have read and understand the Madison City Schools Virtual Option Procedures and the Academic Integrity
Agreement. As a parent/guardian of the above named student, I will support the policies, procedures and
expectations of Madison City Schools Virtual Option as well as the following:

    1. All work submitted will be my student’s work.
    2. ACCESS Virtual Learning policies and procedures.
    3. All course tests and examinations will be at my student’s zoned school with an ACCESS Virtual

         Learning facilitator or teacher.
    4. All Alabama mandated assessments will be taken as proctored examinations at my student’s zoned

         school.
    5. All assignments and deadlines.
    6. Working cooperatively with the teacher and other students is essential.

Parent/Guardian Name (print):__________________________________________________

Parent/Guardian Signature:_________      ____ Date: ______________

                                     81]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[82]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[83]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[84]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[85]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[86]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[87]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[Division I Worksheet

This worksheet is provided to assist you in monitoring your progress in meeting NCAA initial-eligibility standards.
The NCAA Eligibility Center will determine your academic status after you graduate. Remember to check your
high school's list of NCAA-approved courses for the classes you have taken.

            Use the following scale: A = 4 quality points; B = 3 quality points; C = 2 quality points; D = 1 quality point.

English (4 years required)

10/7 Course Title                              Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)

Example: English 9                             .5 A (.5 x 4) = 2

       Total English Units                                                Total Quality Points
    Mathematics (3 years required)
                                               Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)
10/7 Course Title                               1.0 B (1.0 x 3) = 3
       Example: Algebra 1

Total Mathematics Units                                     Total Quality Points

Natural/physical science (2 years required)

10/7 Course Title                              Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)

Total Natural/Physical Science Units                        Total Quality Points

Additional year in English, mathematics or natural/physical science (1 year required)

10/7 Course Title                              Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)

       Total Additional Units                                             Total Quality Points
    Social science (2 years required)          Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)
10/7 Course Title

Total Social Science Units                                               Total Quality Points

Additional academic courses (4 years required)              X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by
                                                                              grade)
10/7 Course Title                              Credit

Total Total Additional Academic Units                           Total Quality Points

Total Quality Points from each subject area /               /=
Total Credits = Core-Course GPA

                                               Quality      / Credits = Core-Course GPA
                                               Points

Core-Course GPA (16 required) 10 core courses must be completed before the seventh semester and seven of the 10 must
be a combination of English, math or natural or physical science for competition purposes.

                                                        88]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[Division II Worksheet

 This worksheet is provided to assist you in monitoring your progress in meeting NCAA initial-eligibility standards.
 The NCAA Eligibility Center will determine your academic status after you graduate. Remember to check your
 high school’s list of NCAA- approved courses for the classes you have taken.
 Use the following scale: A = 4 quality points; B = 3 quality points; C = 2 quality points; D = 1 quality point.

English (3 years required)

Course Title                                   Credit   X Grade =    Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)
Example: English 9                                 .5           A    (.5 x 4) = 2

Total English Units                                                              Total Quality Points

    Mathematics (2 years required)             Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)
Course Title                                    1.0 B (1.0 x 3) = 3
Example: Algebra 1

Total Mathematics Units                                                   Total Quality Points
                                                                     = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)
Natural/physical science (2 years required)

Course Title                                   Credit   X Grade

Total Natural/Physical Science Units                                 Total Quality Points

Additional years in English, math or natural/physical science (3 years required)

Course Title                                   Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)

Total Additional Units                                                           Total Quality Points
                                               Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)
    Social science (2 years required)
Course Title

Total Social Science Units                                           Total Quality Points

Additional academic courses (4 years required)

Course Title                                   Credit X Grade = Quality Points (multiply credit by grade)

Total Additional Academic Units                         /=           Total Quality Points

Total Quality Points from each subject area /           / Credits =  Core-Course GPA
Total Credits = Core-Course GPA

                                               Quality
                                               Points

                                                        89]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[List of Approved Courses from NCAA Clearinghouse

The NCAA has approved the following courses for use in establishing the initial-eligibility certification status of
                                        student-athletes from Madison City Schools.

This list includes all classes approved; some of which are no longer offered by Madison City Schools.

ENGLISH                            SOCIAL STUDIES                       SCIENCE - Continued

ENG 9                              EARLY US HISTORY                     MOLECULAR BIOLOGY

ENG 9/HONORS                       EARLY US HISTORY/HONORS                      PHYSICAL SCIENCE

ENG 10                             ECONOMICS                                    PHYSICS

ENG 10/HONORS                      LAW & SOCIETY                        PHYSICS/H or PREAP

ENG 11                             MODERN US HISTORY                    PRINCIPLES OF BIOMEDICAL SCIENCE

ENG 11/HONORS                      MODERN WORLD HISTORY                 PRINCIPLES OF ENGINEERING

ENG 12                             PSYCHOLOGY                                   AP BIOLOGY

ENG 12/HONORS                      SOCIOLOGY                                    AP CHEMISTRY

CREATIVE WRITING                   US GOVERNMENT                        AP ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE

FRESHMAN COMP                      US HISTORY 1877-PRESENT                      AP PHYSICS 1

INTRO TO COMPOSITION               US HISTORY-1877                      AP PHYSICS MECHANICAL

MYTHS & LEGENDS (.5 credit)        US HISTORY                           AP PHYSICS ELECTRICAL

SPEECH (.5 credit)                 WORLD GEOGRAPHY

AP ENGLISH                         WORLD HISTORY                                ELECTIVES

AP ENGLISH LANGUAGE                WORLD HIS/HONORS                             FRENCH 1

AP ENGLISH LITERATURE              AP ECONOMICS                                 FRENCH 2

                                   AP EUROPEAN HISTORY                          FRENCH 3

MATH                               AP HUMAN GEOGRAPHY                           FRENCH 4

ALGEBRA 1                          AP PSYCHOLOGY                        AP FRENCH LANGUAGE

ALGEBRA 1A (.5 Credit)             AP US GOVERNMENT                             GERMAN 1

ALGEBRA 1B (.5 credit)             AP US GOV & ECON                             GERMAN 2

ALGEBRA 2                          AP US HISTORY                                GERMAN 3

ALGEBRA 2/HONORS                   AP WORLD HISTORY                             GERMAN 4

ALGEBRA II W/TRIG                                                       AP GERMAN LANGUAGE

ALGEBRA II W/TRIG HONORS                                                        LATIN 1

ALGEBRA 3 WITH STATISTICS          SCIENCE                                      LATIN 2

ALGEBRA WITH FINANCE               ASTRONOMY                                    LATIN 3

ALGEBRAIC CONNECTIONS (.5 credit)  BIOLOGY                                      LATIN 4

ANALYTICAL MATHEMATICS             BIOLOGY/H or PREAP                           AP LATIN

CALCULUS                           CHEMISTRY 1                                  SPANISH 1

PRECALCULUS                        CHEMISTRY 2                                  SPANISH 2

PRECALCULUS/HONORS                 CHEMISTRY 1/HONORS or PREAP                  SPANISH 3

DISCRETE MATH                      EARTH/SPACE SCIENCE                          SPANISH 4

GEOMETRY (Practical Geometry)      ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE                AP SPANISH LITERATURE

GEOMETRY 1A (.5 Credit)            FORENSICS                            AP SPANISH LANGUAGE

GEOMETRY 1B (.5 Credit)            GENETICS                                     CHINESE 1

GEOMETRY 1 (.5 Credit)             HUMAN ANATOMY & PHYSICOLOGY                  CHINESE 2

GEOMETRY II (.5 Credit)            HUMAN BODY STRUCTURES AND FUNCTIONS

GEOMETRY HONORS                    HUMAN BODY SYSTEMS                   AP COMPUTER SCIENCE

AP CALCULUS                        MARINE BIOLOGY                       AP COMPUTER SCIENCE PRINCIPLES

AP STATISTICS                      MEDICAL INTERVENTIONS

                    ****Credit Recovery does not satisfy NCAA Requirements****

                                   90]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[Diploma Requirement Checklist Cohort year: 18 19 20 21 Diploma Type: Reg Adv Seal

Student Name: _______________________________________

Date:                                      Grade:      Credits Earned:

English- 4 Credits              AP                     Social Studies- 4 Credits                         AP
                English 9       AP                                          World History                AP
                English 10                                                  US History I                 AP
                English 11                                                  US History II                AP
                English 12                                                  Economics                    AP
                                                                            US Gov
Math - 4 Credits
                Algebra                                Science- 4 Credits                     Chemistry
                                                                            Biology
                Geometry                                                    Physical Science

                Alg II w/ Trig

Required Electives - Cohort 2017+                      Foreign Language - 2 (for Advanced Endorsement)
                Career Prep - 0.5
                Career Prep - 0.5                      3 Credits from Career Tech, World Languages or Fine Arts.
                Health / Fd Hlth Sci                                        (2 credits should be in same area)
                LIFE PE
                                                          91
Madison City Schools Endorsements:
Madison City Advanced Endorsement
Madison City Seal of Academic Distinction

AP COURSES (1= Adv 3=Seal)
        1
        2
        3]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[FERPA NOTICE

FERPA Notice: The Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), a Federal law, requires that Madison
City Schools with certain exceptions, obtain your written consent prior to the disclosure of personally identifiable
information from your child's education records. However, Madison City Schools may disclose appropriately
designated "directory information" without written consent, unless you have advised the District to the contrary in
accordance with District procedures. The primary purpose of directory information is to allow the Madison City
Schools to include this type of information from your child's education records in certain school publications.
Examples include:

    • A playbill, showing your student's role in a drama production;
    • The annual yearbook;
    • Honor roll or other recognition lists;
    • Graduation programs; and
    • Sports activity sheets, such as for wrestling, showing weight and height of team members.

Directory information, which is information that is generally not considered harmful or an invasion of privacy if
released, can also be disclosed to outside organizations without a parent's prior written consent. Outside
organizations include, but are not limited to, companies that manufacture class rings or publish yearbooks. In
addition, two federal laws require local educational agencies (LEAs) receiving assistance under the Elementary
and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (ESEA) to provide military recruiters, upon request, with three directory
information categories—names, addresses and telephone listings—unless parents have advised the LEA that they
do not want their student's information disclosed without their prior written consent. (1)

If you do not want Madison City Schools to disclose directory information from your child's education records
without your prior written consent, you must notify the District in writing by [Sept. 1st ]. Madison City Schools
has designated the following information as directory information:

[Note: an LEA may, but does not have to, include all the information listed below.]
    • Student's name
    • Address
    • Telephone listing
    • Electronic mail address
    • Photograph
    • Date and place of birth
    • Major field of study
    • Dates of attendance
    • Grade level
    • Participation in officially recognized activities and sports
    • Weight and height of members of athletic teams
    • Degrees, honors, and awards received
    • The most recent educational agency or institution attended
    • Student ID number, user ID, or other unique personal identifier used to communicate in electronic
         systems that cannot be used to access education records without a PIN, password, etc. (A
         student's SSN, in whole or in part, cannot be used for this purpose.)

Footnotes:
1.These laws are: Section 9528 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act (20 U.S.C. § 7908), as
amended, and 10 U.S.C. § 503(c), as amended.

                                                                                  92]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[DUAL ENROLLMENT APPROVED COURSES
                                                (Dual Enrollment Under Review)

                                                       MADISON CITY SCHOOLS
                                     DUAL ENROLLMENT COURSES ON THE WEIGHTED GPA SCALE
                 INSTITUTION                                   COURSE                                    GPA
                    Calhoun                           PHY 214, Physics II with Lab                        6.0
                    Calhoun                               MTH 227, Calculus III                           6.0
                    Calhoun                             MTH 237, Linear Algebra                           6.0
                    Calhoun                       ECO 232, Principles of Microeconomics                   6.0
                    Calhoun                            CIS 252, C++ Programming                           6.0
                    Calhoun                             CIS 246, Ethical Hacking                          6.0
                    Calhoun                      CIS 214, Security Analysis (PEN Testing)                 6.0
                    Calhoun                           CIS 282, Computer Forensics                         6.0
                     UAH                                  MA 201, Calculus C                              6.0
                     UAH                          MA 238, Applied Differential Equations                  6.0
                     UAH                                 MA 244, Linear Algebra                           6.0
                     UAH                              MA 330, Foundations of Math                         6.0
                     UAH                       CS 307, Object Oriented Programming in C++                 6.0
                     UAH                  CS 317, Introduction to Design and Analysis of Algorithms       6.0
                     UAH                      CS 413, Introduction to Digital Computer Design             6.0
                     UAH                               CS 470, Computer Networks                          6.0
                     UAH                             CS 485/585, Computer Security                        6.0
                     UAH                              CS 487-01, Database Systems                         6.0
                     UAH                        CS 490, Introduction to Operating Systems                 6.0
                     UAH                           CS 570, Intro to Computer Networks                     6.0




























                                                               93]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[DUAL ENROLLMENT APPROVED COURSES
                                             CALHOUN COMMUNITY COLLEGE
                                                (Dual Enrollment Under Review)


                                                  Calhoun Community College
                                               Dual Enrollment Approved Courses

                                       ENGLISH -- Calhoun                         Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                                    ENG 101 Eng Composition I                           4              1
                                    ENG 102 Eng Composition II                          4              1
                                       SCIENCE -- Calhoun                         Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                                   BIO 103 Principles of Biology I                      4              1
                                   BIO 104 Principles of Biology II                     4              1
                                    PHS 111 Physical Science I                          4              1
                               BIO 201: Human Anatomy & Physiology                      4              1
                                 BIO 202: Anatomy & Physiology II                       4              1
                                    Chemistry 1 (CHM 111-100)                           4              1
                                      Chemistry 2 (CHM 112)                             4              1
                                    PHY 213 Physics I with Lab                          6              1
                                    PHY 214 Physics II with Lab                         6              1
                                        MATH -- Calhoun                           Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                               MTH 100 Intermediate College Algebra                     4              1
                                    MTH 110 Finite Mathmatics                           4              1
                                   MTH 112 PreCalculus Algebra                          4              1
                                 MTH 113 PreCalculus Trigonometry                       4              1
                                        MTH 125 Calculus I                              4              1
                                       MTH 126 Calculus II                              4              1
                                       MTH 227 Calculus III                             6              1
                                      MTH 237 Linear Algebra                            6              1
                                  MTH 265 Elementary Statistics                         4              1
                                 COMPUTER SCIENCE -- Calhoun                      Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                                CIS 146 Microcomputer Applications                      4              1
                                     CIS 252 C++ Programming                            6              1
                                      CIS 246 Ethical Hacking                           6              1
                               CIS 214 Security Analysis (PEN Testing)                  6              1
                                    CIS 282 Computer Forensics                          6              1
                                   SOCIAL SCIENCE -- Calhoun                      Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                                      HIS 121 World History I                           4              1
                                       HIS 201 US History I                             4              1
                                       HIS 202 US History II                            4              1
                               ECO 232 Principles of Microeconomics                     6              1
                                   PSY 200 General Psychology                           4              1
                                    SOC 200 Intro to Sociology                          4              1
                                    PHL 106 Intro to Philosophy                         4              1
                                    PHL 206 Ethics and Society                          4              1
                                 WORLD LANGUAGES --Calhoun                        Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                                      Introductory Spanish 101                          4              1
                                      Introductory Spanish 102                          4              1
                                         EMT-- Calhoun                            Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                               EMS 100 Cardiopulminary Resusitation                     4              1
                              EMS 118 Emergency Medical Technician                      4              1
                           EMS 119 Emergency Medical Technician Clinical                4              1

                                                               94]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[DUAL ENROLLMENT APPROVED COURSES
                                         UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA IN HUNTSVILLE
                                                (Dual Enrollment Under Review)

                                             The University of Alabama in Huntsville
                                               Dual Enrollment Approved Courses
                                          MATH -- UAH                             Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                                   MA 112, PreCalculus Algebra                          4               1
                                 MA 113, PreCalculus Trigonometry                       4               1
                                MA 115, PreCalculus Algebra and Trig                    4               1
                                 MA 120, Calculus with Applications                     4               1
                                        MA 171, Calculus A                              4               1
                                        MA 172, Calculus B                              4              1
                                        MA 201, Calculus C                              6               1
                                MA 238, Applied Differential Equations                  6               1
                                      MA 244, Linear Algebra                            6               1
                                   MA 330, Foundations of Math                          6               1
                                   COMPUTER SCIENCE --UAH                         Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                            CS 100, Intro to Computers and Programming                  4               1
                                   CS 105, Computer Sci Ethics                          4               1
                                   CS102, Intro to C Programming                        4               1
                               CS103, Intro to Programming Using Java                   4               1
                                     CS121, C++ Programming                             4               1
                                 CS214, Intro to Discrete Structures                    4               1
                            CS221, Programming in C++ - Data Structures                 4               1
                             CS307, Object Oriented Programming in C++                  6               1
                       CS317, Introduction to Design and Analysis of Algorithms         6               1
                            CS413, Introduction to Digital Computer Design              6               1
                                    CS470, Computer Networks                            6               1
                                   CS485/585, Computer Security                         6               1
                                   CS487-01: Database Systems                           6               1
                              CS490 Introduction to Operating Systems                   6               1
                                 CS570, Intro to Computer Networks                      6               1
                                     SOCIAL SCIENCES --UAH                        Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                                 PHL 101, Introduction to Philosophy                    4               1
                                 SOC 100, Introduction to Sociology                     4               1
                                    PY 101, General Psychology                          4               1
                                      WH 103, World History                             4               1
                                   WH 104, World History to 1500                        4               1
                                  PSC 101, American Government                          4               1
                               ECN 142 Principles of Macroeconomics                     4               1
                               ECN 143 Principles of Microeconomics                     4               1
                                   HY 221, United States to 1877                        4               1
                                 HY 222, United States Since 1877                       4               1
                                        BUSINESS --UAH                            Rank (4.0, 6.0)    Credit
                             ACC 211, Principles of Financial Accounting                4               1






                                                               95]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[DUAL ENROLLMENT APPROVED COURSES
                                    UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA IN HUNTSVILLE (CON’T)
                                                (Dual Enrollment Under Review)

                                                                                    Rank (4.0,
                SCIENCES --UAH                                                                       Credit
                                                                                       6.0)
                                  AST 107, Survey of Astronomy                          4              1
                                  BYS 119, Principles of Biology                        4              1
                               BYS 491, Undergraduate Special Topic                     4              1
                                BYS 492, Undergraduate Research                         4              1
                            PH 111 and 114 (lab), Physics (co-requisites)               4              1
                                                                                    Rank (4.0,
                                           ART --UAH                                                 Credit
                                                                                       6.0)
                             ARH 100, Survey of Ancient to Medieval Art                 4              1
                           ARH 101, Survey of Renaissance to Modern Art                 4              1
                                    ARS 160, Honors Drawing                             4              1
                                                                                    Rank (4.0,
                                        ENGLISH --UAH                                                Credit
                                                                                       6.0)
                           EH 208-06, Readings in Literature and Culture II             4              1
                    EH 209, Honors Seminar in Readings in Literature and Culture I      4              1
                                  EH 101, Freshman Composition                          4              1
                                  EH 102, English Composition II                        4              1
                                                                                    Rank (4.0,
                                   COMMUNICATIONS --UAH                                              Credit
                                                                                       6.0)
                         CM 113, Introduction to Rhetorical Communications              4              1
                                                                                    Rank (4.0,
                                          MUSIC --UAH                                                Credit
                                                                                       6.0)
                              MU 100, Introduction to Music Literature                  4              1
                                  MU 120, Beginning Voice Class                         4              1
                                                                                    Rank (4.0,
                                   WORLD LANGUAGE --UAH                                              Credit
                                                                                       6.0)
                                 FL101S, Introduccion al espanol I                      4              1
                               WLC 102S, Introduccion al espanol II                     4              1





















                                                               96]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[Superintendent

                                                                              Mr. Robert V. Parker

                                                                              211 Celtic Drive
                                                                              Madison, AL 35758
                                                                              (256) 464-8370
                                                                              Fax: (256) 464-8291
                                                                              www.madisoncity.k12.al.us

Coordinator of Secondary Instruction                                          District College & Career Counselor
                                                                              Mrs. Sheila Roberts
Dr. Heather Donaldson
                                                                              sroberts@madisoncity.k12.al.us
(256) 464-8370 ext. 10351                                                     BJHS (256) 772-2547 ext. 80424
hdonaldson@madisoncity.k12.al.us                                              JCHS (256) 216-5313 ext. 95013

                                 Guidance Department                          Principal
                                                                              Mrs. Sylvia Lambert
Mr. Johnny Fowler
A-Go                                                                          650 Hughes Road
jfowler@madisoncity.k12.al.us                                                 Madison, AL 35758
ext. 80309                                                                    (256) 772-2547
                                                                              Fax: (256) 772-6698
Mrs. Patty Piro                                                               www.bjhs.madisoncity.k12.al.us
P-Z
ppiro@madisoncity.k12.al.us                                                   Ms. Pam Hendrix
ext. 80318                                                                    Gr-O
                                                                              phendrix@madisoncity.k12.al.us
                                                                              ext. 80313

                                                                              Ms. Kathryn Champion
                                                                              College and Career
                                                                              kdchampion@madisoncity.k12.al.us
                                                                              ext. 80212

                                                      Guidance Department     Principal
                                           Guidance Twitter:@JCHSJetAdvisory  Dr. Brian Clayton
Mr. George Cruz
Cohort 2020 and Cohort 2018 A-F                                               11306 County Line Road
gmcruz@madisoncity.k12.al.us                                                  Madison, AL 35756
ext. 95337                                                                    (256)216-5313
                                                                              Fax: (256) 216-5314
                                                                              JCHS Twitter: @James_Clemens
                                                                              www.jchs.madisoncity.k12.al.us

                                                                              Mrs. Lana Meskunas *Summer Contact
                                                                              College and Career
                                                                              llmeskunas@madisoncity.k12.al.us
                                                                              ext. 95274

Mrs. Heather Porter                                                           Mrs. Rosalyn Smith
Cohort 2019 and Cohort 2018 P-Z                                               Cohort 2021 and Cohort 2018 G-O
hporter@madisoncity.k12.al.us                                                 rsmith@madisoncityk12.al.us
ext. 95050                                                                    ext. 95339

                                      97]]></page></pages></Search>
